个人原创字幕
制作人：A Redpill
【译者点评与解读版】
了解更多影片细节，请访问The Matrix Wiki  https://matrix.fandom.com
精彩影评  www.inverse.com/entertainment/matrix-resurrections-aesthetic-adam-egypt-mortimer
黑客帝国系列哲学解析  zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/30606809
【创作声明】
所有点评与解读仅代表译者 A Redpill 个人观点
译者已于一个月内从头翻译了The Matrix系列5部作品  因而对此系列的熟悉恐怕超过了多数观影者
另外  本字幕制作中参考了大量中外评析  尽可能做到言出有据  欢迎读者批评吐槽！
以满分10.0计  译者个人对The Matrix 1~4的评分依次为：9.4，9.3，8.8，8.4
译者对The Matrix 4的评价可概括为：
颠覆彻底  讽喻深刻  细节丰富  设定拓宽
节奏推动拉跨  工具人较多
另外，多数人唯一能看懂的“大场面”大概是被刻意削弱了: )
在2003年，三部曲上映后，那本出现在Matrix 1中的《拟像与仿真》的作者——法国哲学家Jean Baudrillard这样批评道：
“《黑客帝国》是那种可能是由矩阵自己制作的关于矩阵的电影……基本上，它在世界范围内的传播与电影本身串通一气。”
换句话说：如果真的有矩阵，它最好的策略就是通过制作电影《黑客帝国》，掩盖自己实际的存在！
这也许正是Matrix 4剧情灵感的来源
于是，Matrix 4中，三部曲的炫酷美学被它的创作者坚决粉碎
拉娜·沃卓斯基使用反美学和刻意丑化来讽刺当今现实，并质疑《黑客帝国》系列的美学可能发挥了矩阵本身的作用
“当你攻击主流审美时，人们总是讨厌它，”拉娜在 2014 年曾说，“人们会出现暴力的感觉”——Matrix 4上映后的恶评如潮应证了这一预言
-希克，我进去了  -舰长
-Seq, I'm in.   -Captain.
模态 101 违规/用户侵权
主机报警 KIWW/12:15
你是对的
You were right.
观景窗果真是个程序窗口
The skylight was a window pane.
追踪程序运行中：
我受到了严重的干扰
I've got serious interference.
奇怪  这儿运行着某种模态
Weird.  It's some kind of Modal.
看起来像旧代码
Looks like old code.
感觉好熟悉啊
It feels really familiar.
标记一下位置  我会投影去支援你
Drop a pin.  I'll signal for backup.
-我要去查看一下  -巴格斯？
-I'm gonna check it out.  -Bugs?
要是被将军知道我们一直在摸鱼……
If the general finds out we've been fishing...
就看一眼不碍事儿的
A quick peek can't hurt.
听见那个声音了吗？
Did you hear that?
该死  我觉得我们的信号被追踪了
Shit.  I think our signal was traced.
巴格斯，这感觉像是个陷阱
Bugs, this feels like a trap.
巴格斯！
Bugs!
注意墙边的雨水→
都是银灰色的代码雨
矩阵的第一个镜头是街头水坑，如镜子般倒映着一队特警缓慢接近，惊叹而有力
然后一只警靴踩在水坑上，摧毁了它脚下的美丽——镜子被打碎了
这种对自身美学的攻击是蓄意的
不许动！ 不要动！
Freeze!  Do not move!
否则我们会开枪的！
We will shoot!
慢慢把手举起来
Very slowly, raise your hands.
这帮人又来了
Here we go.
嘿，你要去哪儿？
Hey, where are you going?
你已经被警告过了，警督
You were warned, Lieutenant.
我想我们还是对付得了一个小姑娘的
I think we can handle one little girl.
你们这是在浪费时间
You're wasting your time!
我的人马上就把她带下来了
My men are bringing her down now.
不，警督……
No, Lieutenant,
你的人已经死了
your men are already dead.
希克，你还在吗
Seq, you with me?
这个旧代码在不断地崩溃
This old code keeps crashing.
你的投影也在崩溃  切换到音频吧
Your projection's breaking up.  Switch to audio.
巴格斯，这直接违反了
Bugs, this is a direct violation
将军制定的流程
of the general's protocols.
我知道，我知道
I know, I know.
但是这里有事要发生
But something is happening here.
一些重要的事
Something important.
哦，该死
Oh, fuck.
我们知道接下来会发生的事
We know what happens next.
她会把他们打的落花流水
She kicks their ass.
现在她要打个电话
Now she makes a call.
这条线路被追踪到了
The line was traced.
-然后……  -然后她会拼命逃跑
-And then...   -Then she runs for her life.
特工来了吗？
Are there any agents?
我们知道这个故事
We know this story.
一切就是这样开始的
This is how it all began.
天杀的
God damn it.
这里也是他开始的地方
This is where he began.
你觉得这个模态是一个循环吗？  或是原地重演？
You're thinking this Modal is a loop?  Or a treadmill?
一系列场景演化着这个程序，来做什么的 ？
Some sort of sequencer evolving a program to do what?
我不知道
I don't know.
但我会找到答案的
But I'm going to find out.
好吧
All right.
如此似曾相识，但显然又都不对了
So deja vu and yet it's obviously all wrong.
为什么要用旧代码来反映新情节呢？
Why use old code to mirror something new?
我也不知道
I don't know.
如果那应该是崔妮蒂的话，
If that's supposed to be Trinity,
事情不该是这样的
that's not what happens.
也许这不是我们以为的那个故事
Maybe this isn't the story we think it is.
巴格斯，你得离开这儿
Bugs, you have to get out of here.
这肯定是个陷阱
It's gotta be a trap.
该死
Shit.
呃...
Uh...
各位继续
You all carry on.
就当我没来过
As you were.
我只是想要……
I'm just gonna...
离开这里
see myself out.
杀了她
Kill her.
（灯牌）
谨以此片
献给
喜欢吃屎的人
哦，希克！
Oh, Seq!
-你为什么要救我？  -你先说
-Why did you save me?  -You first.
你是谁 你从哪儿来
Who are you? Where did you come from?
好吧
Okay.
我叫巴格斯
My name is Bugs.
和“兔八哥”一个名
As in "Bunny."
Bugs Bunny即著名卡通人物“兔八哥”
也指一种监听技术
And tech that listens.
Bug 作动词是“窃听”，作名词是“漏洞”
你知道这里一个“模态”吗？
Do you know this is a Modal?
什么是“模态”？
What's a Modal?
就是一种用于演化程序的仿真
It's a simulation used to evolve programs.
你知不知道自己其实是...
Do you understand that you are...
数字监测程序？
digital sentience?
Matrix 1中出现过sentient program/sentience  均特指特工程序
我知道我是什么
I know what I am.
就如同我知道我的工作
Just like I know my job
是追捕和消灭“合成体”
is to hunt down and destroy synthients.
syntients指与人类合作的机器/程序
比如说 你
Like you.
然而……
And yet...
我们却来到了这儿
Here we are.
我们到了这儿
其他特工不知道这个房间吗？
The other agents don't know about this room?
你是怎么找到这里的？
How'd you find it?
从来没有人进过钥匙店，
No one was ever in the key shop,
所以我就开始寻找
so I started looking.
你观察得越多，发现得越多
More you looked, the more you found.
正如我的人生故事
Story of my life.
怎么？
What?
我感觉我知道这个房间
I feel like I know this room.
超越大脑皮层公司
托马斯·A·安德森
初级程序员
签发日期 1996/05/28
我的天
Holy shit.
这是他的公寓
This is his apartment.
你是指托马斯·安德森的？
You mean Thomas Anderson's?
我到处都找过了  没有这个人
I searched everywhere.  He doesn't exist.
他很久之前就不再是托马斯了……
He stopped being Thomas a long time ago, but...
但是，也许你知道他的真名
maybe you know him by his real name.
尼奥
Neo.
你真的知道
You do.
噢 好吧
Oh, okay.
呃……
Uh...
真是难以置信，这么多年过去了
I can't believe this, after all these years.
你知道，大多数人都认为尼奥已经死了
You see, most people think that Neo is dead.
但我知道他没有死
But I know he's not.
因为我见过他本人
Because I've seen him.
在哪？
Where?
这不是我几句话就能解释的，但是……
It's not something I can explain easily, but...
他看着我的那一刻
But the moment he looked at me,
我觉得有某种东西……
I felt something...
打开了我的心扉
unlock my mind.
好吧
Okay.
类似的事情也发生在了我身上
Something like that happened to me.
我看到了那种图案……
I saw this pattern...
它简直无处不在
and it was everywhere.
我们看不见它，却又都被困在里面——
We can't see it, but we're all trapped inside
这些怪异的、不断重复的循环
these strange, repeating loops.
不知怎的，我在镜子里看见了它
Somehow I saw it in the mirror.
虽然它一闪而过，但就像你说的
Just a flicker, but it was like you said.
突然间，我明白了：
And suddenly I understood.
这不是真实世界
This is not the real world.
人生中第一次，我感受到了真实的意义
For the first time, I felt real purpose.
我知道了我是谁
I knew who I was
以及我必须做的事情
and what I had to do.
你到底是谁？
Who are you?
你必须要做什么？
What do you have to do?
我就是……
I am...
墨菲斯
Morpheus.
我必须要找到尼奥
And I have to find Neo.
墨菲斯
Morpheus.
好吧  好吧
Okay.  Okay.
哦，我的天！
Oh, my God!
我得带你离开这里
I have to get you out of here.
我得弄清楚是谁建造了这个模态
I need to figure out who built this Modal.
好吧，跟我来
Okay, come with me.
你得做好离开的准备   必须得真正准备好
You have to be ready to leave.  You have to be really ready.
如果你还没准备好，
And if you're not,
如果你依然认为自己属于这里……
if you think that this is where you belong...
你管这个叫做“选择”？
You call this a choice?
哦，说实话，当有人给我这些药丸的时候，
Oh, honestly, when somebody offered me these things,
我还沉浸在二元对立的观念里
I went off on binary conceptions of the world
于是说，我才不要吞下
and said there was no way I was swallowing
这种象征着抹除人生的药丸
some symbolic reduction of my life.
这里是奈奥比亲手解放了巴格斯
然后拿着药片的女人笑了
And the woman with the pills laughed
因为我搞错了关键
'cause I was missing the point.
什么关键？
What point?
选择其实是一种错觉
The choice is an illusion.
你早就知道自己要做什么了
You already know what you have to do.
告诉我真相
Truth.
好的
Okay.
这儿有一栋老建筑
There's an old building
Matrix 1中Lafayette酒店正是墨菲斯等人的总部
尼奥在此吃下红药丸，后来也在此遇袭、墨菲斯被捕
有一扇观景窗和很多楼梯
with a skylight and lots of stairs.
拉斐特酒店
The Lafayette.
那四个后门中有一个通向那里
One of the four back doors leads there.
噢
Oh.
-不要抗拒  -哇哦，怎么回事？
-Don't fight it.   -Whoa, what's happening?
保持呼吸
Keep breathing.
人类和程序抽取的原理
Extraction works pretty much the same
基本上都差不多
for humans and programs.
哎哟
Ouch.
啊
Ah.
好的
Okay.
-嘿  -嗨
-Hey.  -Hey.
我还从没戴过不同的眼镜呢
I've never worn different glasses before.
是的，看起来挺好的  是哪扇门？
Yeah, looks good.  Which door?
-好像是这个……  -好的
-It's gotta be...  -Okay.
怀特特工
Agent White.
史密斯特工？
Agent Smith?
快走！
Go!
希克！ 能听见我吗？
Seq!  Can you hear me?
巴格斯！  我还以为你失踪了
Bugs! I thought I lost you.
你能把我们带到窗口那里吗？
Can you get us to the window pane?
巴格斯！巴格斯！他可是个特工！
Bugs! Bugs! He's an agent!
那扇窗！ 赶紧的！
That window!  Go hard!
这是通过程序窗口脱离模态，进入矩阵
（杰出交互式游戏设计奖
托马斯·安德森）
尼奥在设计金色的游戏世界
同时注意左边的金色屏幕
BINARY  游戏《二元对立》
屏幕画面和结尾崔尼蒂眼中金色代码的大厦很相似
（1999 年度游戏
黑客帝国
神机游戏公司）
什么……
What the...
警告：边界突破  ALERT-PERIMETER BREACH
模态错误:  设备：O盘：一段非法记忆  进入  MODAL ERROE: ON DEVICE O: An illegal memory ACCESS
错误：丢失文件“墨菲斯-烟雾弹”.exe/“城市之心”旅馆  ERROR MISSING FILE "MORPH-BLD.EXE"/"HEART O'THE CITY"
什么鬼？
What the hell?
出什么事了？
Something wrong?
呃……只是一个小崩溃
Uh... Just a little crash.
早上好，鲍比  早上好，哥们
Morning, Bobbi.  Morning, dude.
多么美好的一天啊  是吧？
What a beautiful day to be alive.  Am I right?
-出问题了吗？  -他丢了一些文件
-Problem?   -He lost something.
这是旧的《黑客帝国》代码么？
Is this old Matrix code?
尼奥警惕地关掉了模态文件，切换回工作屏幕——金色代码的世界
一个小小的模态实验
A little Modal experiment.
为《二元对立》做的？
For Binary?
(短信提醒：下午4点预算会议)
-我想来杯咖啡  -咖啡  好的，走吧
-I need a coffee.  -Coffee. Yes, stat!
我来买单
I'm buying.
仿真咖啡馆
SIMULATTE
红灯亮起 请勿转弯
（双关：不要选择红药丸）
NO TURN ON RED
我不是想拍你马屁，
I'm not trying to blow smoke up your ass,
但我第一次玩《黑客帝国》三部曲的时侯，我简直是被震撼了
but the first time I played the trilogy, I was shook.
自由意志与命运之间的悖论
The paradox between free will and destiny.
桌面上是”真实外表“的倒影
我们只能在算法的驱动下……
Are we all just algorithms
做自己该做的事
doing what we're supposed to do
我们能摆脱自己的程序设定吗？
or can we escape our programming?
真是天才啊，还有游戏的背景，BT的配音
Genius, inside the context of the game, BT dubs.
嘿，我有没有告诉过你，它差点就占据我的生活？
Hey, did I tell you it took over my life?
我上七年级时还因此考不及格呢
Yeah.  I failed the seventh grade.
你的游戏差点就把我毁了
Your game almost ruined me.
-你是说过了  -然而我们还是到了这里
-So you've said.  -Yet here we are.
你告诉我，安德森先生，
You tell me, Mr. Anderson,
这到底是自由意志
is it free will
还是命运的安排？
or destiny?
哦，是的
Oh, yeah.
她来了
There she is.
真特么是个熟透的蜜桃
Total f-ing MILF.
扎心啊  听着，我很抱歉
Daggers.  Look, I'm sorry.
我真是不合时宜  我是被机器养大的
I'm a geek.  I was raised by machines.
也许你该走了
Maybe you should go.
不，拜托  我……我保证，我会表现好的
No, please. I... I promise, best self.
会表现好的
Best self.
当然了
Sure.
你和她说过话么？
You ever talk to her?
告诉你吧
Tell you what.
为了感谢你为我所做的一切，让我也帮你个忙吧
For all you've done for me, let me do this for you.
裘德，不  别这样
Jude, no.  Stop.
-打扰一下  打扰一下  -谢谢
-Excuse me.  Excuse me.  -Thanks.
你好  呃...
Hi.  Um...
我知道这有点儿唐突
I know this is all a bit extemporaneous.
我叫裘德·加拉赫
I'm Jude Gallagher.
我在一家“神机”游戏公司工作
I work for a game company called Deus Machina.
嗨，裘德，我是蒂芙尼
Hi, Jude, I'm Tiffany.
蒂芙尼  哇哦  好意外的名字
Tiffany.  Wow.  Didn't see that coming.
-我妈喜欢奥黛丽·赫本  -裘德
-Mom loved Audrey Hepburn.  -Jude.
奥黛丽赫本主演过《蒂凡尼的早餐》<i>Breakfast at Tiffany's</i>
这位是我非常要好的朋友，托马斯·安德森
Oh, and this is my very good friend, Thomas Anderson.
他可是位货真价实的名人
He is a bona fide famous person
被大多数人公认为
and considered by most to be
当代最伟大的游戏设计师
the greatest game designer of our generation.
实在是不好意思
I'm sorry about this.
-裘德……  -就跟她聊聊呗
-Jude...  -Just talk to her.
嗨，托马斯  大家都叫我“蒂芙”
Hi, Thomas.  Everyone calls me "Tiff."
嗨
Hi.
我们见过吗？
Have we met?
呃，我们都常来这家咖啡馆
Uh, we both come here.
-我可以吃你的早餐包吗？ -嘿！
-Can I have your morning bun?  -Hey!
你是想要泡我妈还是怎么着？
Are you trying to ball my mom or what?
布兰登！
Brandon!
我能咬一口吗？
Can I have one bite?
宝贝  怎么啦？ 我们要迟到了
Babe! What's going on?  We're gonna be late.
这是<i>JOHN WIKE</i>的导演查德·斯塔赫斯基
他也是《黑客帝国》三部曲中，尼奥的动作替身
这是我丈夫，查德
This is my husband, Chad.
-很高兴认识你  -嗨
-Nice to meet you.  -Hey.
宝贝，我们得送凯莉去训练了
Babe, we gotta get Callie to practice.
是的  不好意思
Right.  Sorry.
来吧，孩子们  我们走吧
Come on, kids.  Let's move out.
资源：未检测到模态101  ASSETS: MODAL 101 UNDETECTED
101号房间是尼奥在Matrix 1中的公寓，隐喻The One
什么？
What?
模态101：文件已被清除  MODAL 101: FILE PURGED
抱歉  呃，老板找你
Sorry. Uh, it's the boss.
“数十亿人就在这里过活……
"Billions of people just living out their lives...
一无所知”
oblivious."
我一直都很喜欢这句台词
I always loved that line.
是你写的，对吧？
You wrote that one, yeah?
每次我站在这儿，
Every time I stand here,
我都在想，我-的-天
I mean, O-M-G.
这儿太完美了，一定是假的
It's so perfect, it's gotta be fake.
对吧？
Right?
嗯
Yeah.
没错
Sure.
坐吧
Have a seat.
抽烟吗？
Smoke?
我还以为你戒掉了
I thought you quit.
我只是戒掉称之为“习惯”了
I quit calling it a habit.
现在它只是“罪恶的欢娱”
Now it's just a guilty pleasure.
噢  也许我可以让这件事不那么难以启齿……
Oh.  Maybe I can make this easy for you.
我知道《二元对立》预算超支了
I know Binary is over budget.
但我不是要说《二元对立》，汤姆  是个更大的事儿
This is not about Binary, Tom.  It's bigger than that.
它关系到我们的未来
This is about our future,
而且鉴于我们的过去，这事儿挺棘手的
which is a sticky subject, given our past.
你是指什么？
What do you mean?
你的心理治疗怎么样了？
How's the therapy?
还好
Good.
（你的精神崩溃）还有过……
Any...
再发作吗？
episodes?
没有
No.
那太好了
That's terrific.
听着，汤姆，我知道我们一直存在分歧
Look, Tom, I know we've always had our differences.
你是怎么形容我们的第一次见面来着？
What did you say about our first meeting?
就像是在进行一场FBI审讯
We had all the chemistry of an FBI interrogation.
但是看看这里
But look at this place.
我们一起
We did this.
成就了这一切
Together.
是的
Yeah.
但现在呢？
Now what?
时代变了  市场不景气了
Things have changed.  The market's tough.
我相信你能理解，为什么我们敬爱的
I'm sure you can understand why our beloved
母公司，华纳兄弟
parent company, Warner Bros,
决定要制作黑客帝国三部曲的续集
has decided to make a sequel to the trilogy.
什么？
What?
他们告诉我，无论有没有我们，他们都会这么做
They informed me they're gonna do it with or without us.
我觉得他们不能这么干
I thought they couldn't do that.
噢，他们可以
Oh, they can.
而且他们明确表示
And they made it clear
如果我们不合作的话，他们就终止我们的合同
they'll kill our contract if we don't cooperate.
真的？
Really?
我知道，你说过这个故事已经结束了，但是……
I know you said the story was over for you, but...
“故事”不就是这样吗
that's the thing about stories.
它们永远都不会真正结束，对吧？
They never really end, do they?
我们在讲的故事还是老一套
We're still telling the same stories we've always told,
只不过换了不同的名字，不同的面孔
just with different names, different faces
而且，不得不说我还有点激动呢
and I have to say I'm kind of excited.
这么多年之后
After all these years,
又将回到一切的起点
to be going back to where it all started.
回到矩阵
Back to The Matrix.
我已经和市场部谈过了……
I've spoken to Marketing...
汤姆？
Tom?
我在
Yeah.
你没事儿吧？
Are you all right?
是的
Yeah.
你当时有什么感受吗？
What were you feeling at that point?
Feelings是分析师的口头禅，他相信，人类是靠与环境的交互中产生的稳定/不稳定的感性体验来构建“真实”的
因此，他不断教导尼奥“用手指轻触”感受到的东西才是”真实“的，而这恰恰是谎言
我当时是什么感受？
What was I feeling?
我觉得，要么是我又精神崩溃了
I felt either I'm having a mental breakdown again
要么是，我其实活在一个电脑生成的虚拟现实中
or I'm living inside a computer-generated reality
那个世界已经囚禁了我……
that has imprisoned me...
又一次地
again.
还真是没得选啊
Not much of a choice.
没有
No.
也许并不需要这样二选一
Maybe it's not as binary as that.
也许还有其他方式可以解读发生的事情
Maybe there are other ways to understand what happened.
是啊
Yeah.
托马斯，你是个自杀幸存者
Thomas, you are a suicide survivor
且天生极具想象力
gifted with a powerful imagination.
这两个因素结合起来
Those facts have combined
在你的生活中制造了危险的虚构场景
to create dangerous fictions in your life.
就在昨天，你和你的商业合伙人
Yesterday, you walked into a meeting
开了个会
with your business partner
他打了你个措手不及
and he ambushed you,
他要求你做一个，你说过永远不会再做的游戏
demanding you make a game you said you would never make.
这个袭击有效地夺走了你的话语权
This attack effectively took away your voice.
他的言语暴力激怒了你，你就在想象中予以回击
His violence triggered you and your mind fought back.
你想象他被封住了嘴，因为他夺走了你的话语权
You did to him what he was doing to you.
我们已经讨论过，这种适应性的愤怒
We've talked about the value
对愈合创伤的益处了
of adaptive anger in healing trauma.
它远不是你早期的那种精神崩溃的重演
Far from suggesting a repeat of your initial breakdown,
我相信这一次发作
I believe this episode
显示出你具有健康的自我保护能力
demonstrates healthy self-protection.
更重要的是，我还记得对你来说
And more importantly, I remember how hard
分享这类事情有多么的困难
it was for you to share something like this.
这就意味着我们已经取得很大的进展
Which tells me just how far we've come.
你需要我再开点药吗？
Do you need a refill on your prescription?
行吧
Yeah.
首先，我知道每个人都和我一样……
First of all, I know I speak for everyone
都想说：我真是太、太兴奋了，
when I say that I'm so, so excited
能参与到这个，一度是行业革命者的
to be working on a game that was such a...
游戏的开发中
well, game changer.
现在，放在你们面前的
Now, the packet in front of you
是我们焦点小组的调查报告
has our focus group research.
在里面，你会发现各种详细划分
Inside, you'll find the breakdown
包括 品牌有关的关键词
including keyword association with the brand.
排在前两位的是“原创性”和“新鲜感”
The top two being "originality" and "fresh,"
我认为它们是你们最需要牢记的事，
which I think are great things to keep in mind
在开发《黑客帝国4》的时候
as you begin working on Matrix 4.
♪ 背景音乐 ♪
White Rabbit
《追逐白兔》
歌手：Jefferson Airplane
或许还有更多要牢记的呢！
And who knows how many more?
是什么让《黑客帝国》与众不同？ 它影响了你的头脑
What made Matrix different? It effed with your head.
说到点子上了
On point.
人们想让我们，在他们无趣的空间里
People want us up in their grey space,
点亮一盏让他们卧槽连连的灯
switching their synaptic "WTF" light on.
♪ 一颗药丸让你变大 ♪
♪ 一颗药丸让你变小 ♪
♪ One pill makes you larger and ♪
♪ One pill makes you small... ♪
是什么让《黑客帝国》与众不同？ 它影响了你的头脑
What made  Matrix different? It effed with your head.
人们希望我们进入他们无趣的空间
People want us up in their grey space,
打开他们脑洞中
switching their synaptic.
那盏“这到底是怎么回事儿？”的灯
"What the hell is going on here?" light on.
♪ 妈妈给你的那些东西 ♪
♪ 根本毫无用处 ♪
♪ And the ones that mother gives you ♪
♪ Don't do anything at all ♪
我不太喜欢第一部作品，和有些人一样
I didn't love the first one, like some of you.
而且坦率地说，我对于任何需要
And, frankly, I've got zero tolerance
大纲和马克笔的东西都零容忍
for anything that requires a syllabus and a highlighter.
我喜欢的游戏是大制作，大场面，没那么多废话的
I like my games big, loud and dumb.
译者吐槽：这里<i>JOHN WICK</i>条条中枪（无贬义）
我们需要枪！ 大量的枪
We need guns!  Lots of guns.
《黑客帝国》意味着暴乱
Matrix means mayhem.
♪ 去问问爱丽丝吧 ♪
♪ Go ask Alice ♪
无脑的动作戏不符合品牌形象
Mindless action is not on-brand.
她说的没错
She's right.
《黑客帝国》是思想高潮   是包裹着闪亮的……
Matrix is mind-porn.  Philosophy in shiny...
-紧身皮衣的哲学  -是的
-tight PVC.  -Yeah.
理念是新的“性感”
Ideas are the new "sexy."
♪ 向他们讲述着一只抽着水烟袋的大青虫 ♪
♪ 给了你这个忠告 ♪
♪ Tell 'em a hookah smoking caterpillar ♪
♪ Has given you the call to ♪
埋葬真实要比摆脱梦境容易得多
It is much simpler to bury reality than it is to dispose of dreams
这是一本《爱丽丝镜中奇遇》（不要再误解为《爱丽丝漫游奇境》了）
镜子是Matrix 4中贯穿始终的元素，镜子/玻璃中映出了矩阵的真相（代码雨/DSI），也是连接现实世界与矩阵的出入口
“情节镜像”也显然被贯彻始终：从开场“崔尼蒂”竟被特工打败，到最后是崔尼蒂拉住了尼奥，无不如此
♪ 记住睡鼠说的 ♪
♪ Remember what the dormouse said ♪
显然《黑客帝国》是关于……
Obviously The Matrix is about...
-跨政治学  -隐秘法西斯主义
-...trans-politics.  -Crypto-fascism.
它是一个隐喻……
It's a metaphor...
针对资本主义的剥削
...of capitalist exploitation.
♪ 如果你去追逐白兔 ♪
♪ 你知道你会掉进洞中 ♪
♪ And if you go chasing rabbits ♪
♪ And you know you're going to fall ♪
这不能是另一次重启、翻新和照搬……
This cannot be another reboot, retread, regurgitated...
为什么不能？  重启卖得好啊
Why not?  Reboots sell.
吃牛排的情节可能是照应Matrix 1中，叛徒Cypher说：
我知道牛排是不存在的，矩阵让我的脑子认为它多汁又可口。但我宁愿无知
这里，尼奥迟疑了一下便把牛肉送入口中，可能只是瞬间地怀疑了矩阵
♪ 当棋盘上的所有人 ♪
♪ 起身告诉你路在何方 ♪
♪ When the men on the chessboard ♪
♪ Get up and tell you where to go ♪
我们在错误的兔子洞里跌的太深了，伙计们
We are so far down the wrong rabbit hole, here, people.
你和一和别人说起《黑客帝国》……   黑客帝国...
You say Matrix to anyone...  You say Matrix...
黑客帝国... 黑客帝国... 黑客帝国...
Matrix... Matrix... Matrix...
他们就会想到这个……
...this is what they see.
♪ 记住啊…… ♪
♪ Remember... ♪
让我用一个词来概括我们的目标吧
Allow me to sum up our goal in a single word.
子弹时间！ 子弹时间！
Bullet time!  Bullet time!
这是两个词
That's two words.
♪ 当正常的逻辑和比例大小 ♪
♪ 在童话世界里草率消失 ♪
♪ When logic and proportion ♪
♪ Have fallen sloppy dead ♪
我们需要一种新的“子弹时间”
We need a new "bullet time."
♪ 白骑士在背后议论纷纷 ♪
♪ 红皇后尖叫“砍掉她的脑袋！” ♪
♪ And the White Knight is talking backwards ♪
♪ And the Red Queen's "off with her head!" ♪
我们需要再次革命游戏行业
We need to revolutionize gaming again.
再次革命游戏行业
Revolutionize gaming again!
♪ 记住睡鼠说了些啥 ♪
♪ Remember what the dormouse said ♪
♪ 填饱你的头脑 ♪
♪ Feed your head ♪
下午好，蒂芙
Afternoon, Tiff.
来杯乌什？
The ushe?
知道吗，斯克罗斯，我要来点狂野的
You know what, Skroce? I'm going wild.
今天我想来杯科塔多
I'll have a cortado today.
放飞自我吧
Fly that freak flag.
介意我帮你拿吗？
Mind if I get that?
哦，嗨
Oh, hi.
嗨
Hi.
我记得我想要一个家庭
I remember wanting a family,
但这可能是因为……
but was that because
女人就应该想要这个？
that's what women are supposed to want?
你怎么知道，某些事是你自己想要的，
How do you know if you want something yourself
还是，你的成长环境决定了你，才让你想要这个
or if your upbringing programmed you to want it?
直译为：你想做的某些事，到底是出于个人意愿呢，还是因为，你的培养者“编程”了你，让你想去做
嗯
Mmm.
我给了我的心理分析师一大笔钱
I pay my analyst a lot of money
就是为了回答我的这类问题的
to answer such questions for me.
聪明啊
Smart.
我也应该接受更多的治疗
I should get more therapy
但说实话，我太他妈的累了
but honestly, I'm too goddamn tired.
带孩子很累人的，你知道吗
Kids are exhausting, you know?
我不知道  我没有孩子
No.  Never had kids.
哦是的，我知道
Oh, right, I knew that.
不好意思  我谷歌过你
Sorry. I googled you.
那么，成为一名闻名世界的游戏设计师是什么感觉？
So, what's it like being a world-famous game designer?
-一定很棒  -呃...
-Must be amazing.  -Uh...
会在工作上花很长时间……
A lot of hours.
有时侯感觉很棒
Sometimes it is amazing.
但大多数时候……
Most times...
我不清楚
I don't know.
但就是你制作了《黑客帝国》  连我都听说过呢
But you made The Matrix.  Even I've heard of that.
是的  我们都是为了让孩子们开心
Yeah.  We kept some kids entertained.
那么，值得吗？
So, worth it?
我可以问一些关于那个游戏的事情吗？
Can I ask something about your game?
当然可以
Sure.
游戏的主角是基于你自己吗？
Did you base your main character on yourself?
在他身上有很多我的影子
There is a lot of me in him.
也许有点太多了
Maybe a little too much.
我能问问你另外一件事吗？
Can I ask you something else?
请吧
Please.
你的游戏里有个女人
There's a woman in your game.
崔妮蒂
Trinity.
也是个奇怪的巧合，对吧？
Which is a weird coincidence also, right?
老天，是的
God, yeah.
我喜欢她
I like her.
-我喜欢崔妮蒂  -啊
-I like Trinity.  -Ah.
我还喜欢她的杜卡迪
And I dig her Ducati.
另一个巧合  我也喜欢摩托车
Another coincidence.  I love motorcycles.
我和我朋友库什事实上自己造了它们
My friend Kush and I actually build them.
真的？
Really?
你有你的分析师，我有我的摩托车
You have your analyst, I have my bikes.
所以，我看着游戏里崔妮蒂的画面
So, I was looking at images from your game.  At Trinity.
然后，我给查德看了一个场景，
Well, I showed Chad a scene,
我问他“所以，你觉得怎么样？”
and I was like, "So, what do you think?"
他一直没领会到，
He didn't get it until I said,
直到我说 “你不觉得她长得很像我吗？”
"Don't you think she looks like me?"
你知道他什么反应吗？
You know what he did?
他笑了
He laughed.
我也笑了，就当它只是个玩笑
And I laughed too, like it was a joke.
怎么可能不是笑话呢，对吧？
How could it not be, right?
这让我很生气
Made me so angry.
我恨自己跟他一起笑了
I hated myself for laughing.
我真想狠狠地踹他一脚
I wanted to kick him so hard.
但也不能太狠
Not too hard.
也许刚好能踹烂他的下巴就行
Maybe just hard enough to break his jaw off.
现在，你是不是挺后悔
And right now, you're probably regretting
和我坐在一起
sitting down with me.
这是我很长时间以来，做过的最好的事情了
This is the best thing I've done in a long time.
我得接个电话
I have to take this.
嗨，我是蒂芙
Hi, this is Tiff.
哦，天呐  不
Oh, God, no.
我马上过去
I'll be right there.
我最小的孩子，把一块乐高积木塞进了鼻子里
My, uh, youngest stuck a Lego up his nose.
哦
Oh.
我得走了
I gotta go.
希望能再次见到你
I hope I see you again.
现在报导一则
There has been a report
紧急情况
of an emergency.
请保持冷静，前往最近的出口
Proceed calmly to the nearest exit
并立即离开大楼
and leave the building immediately.
发生了什么事儿
What's going on?
我们可能只是被一些14岁小孩儿摆了一道
We probably just got swatted by some 14-year-old.
是啊，有人被最近的更新激怒了
Yeah, someone pissed about the latest update.
或者他们本来就是一群混蛋
Or they're just a dick.
请前往出口处  大楼正在疏散中
Please move to the exits.  Building's being evacuated.
你有一条新信息  点击查看
你好 尼奥
如果你想得到问题的答案，就去大厅尽头的那扇门
现在就去
你是谁？
你懂的
裘德？
Jude?
裘德
Jude!
终于
At last.
啊
Ah.
我不太确定前作里有没有回电
I wasn't too sure about the callback,
但是，知道吧，这种诱惑真是很难抗拒
but, you know, it was hard to resist.
什么？
What?
墨菲斯·乌诺  出现在窗边
Morpheus Uno.  Reveal at the window.
闪电交加，雷声滚滚，带着剧院效果
Lightning, thunder and theater.
终于
At last.
这么多年之后，我又回来了
All these years later, here's me,
从一个厕所的隔间里漫步出来
strolling out of a toilet stall.
算是悲剧还是闹剧？
Tragedy or farce?
我知道你
I know you.
不是每天都能见到自己的造物主的
Not every day you meet your maker.
这不可能发生
This can't be happening.
哦，这当然是真的
Oh, most definitely is.
你不可能是我编码的角色
You can't be a character I coded.
百分百真实
100% natural.
怎么会这样？
How?
你需要的所有解释，都在这儿
All the explanation you need.
哦
Oh.
不
No.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
哇哦  你说“不”是啥意思？
Whoa, whoa, whoa.  What do you mean, "no"?
你就想要这样，你自己干的  这都是你的主意啊
You wanted this, you did this.  This was your idea.
那只是一个测试  一个实验
It was a test.  An experiment.
一个实验？
An experiment?
你把我放进一个那么小的模态里，
You put me in a tiny-ass Modal,
让我一次次地碰壁，
left me to bang my head till
直到我差点掉了脑袋，就为了找你
I nearly lost my shit searching for you
就为了做个实验？
as an experiment.
-出口正在崩溃  -他还没有吃药
-The exit's breaking down.  -He hasn't taken the pill.
什么？  没时间了
What?  There's no time.
我知道，我知道  他还需要点时间
I know, I know.  He's having a moment.
他知道黑进那面镜子有多难吗？
Does he know how hard it was to hack that mirror?
还开着呢
Still open.
这...  这不可能是真的
This...  This can't be real.
目标锁定  我们找到他了
Target acquired.  We got him.
这不是真的
This isn't happening.
这都是我脑子里的  都是我脑子里的
It's in my mind.  It's in my mind.
嘿，就你！ 停下！ 别动！
Hey, you!  Stop!  Hold it!
这不可能是真的
This can't be happening.
不许动！ 别动！
Freeze!  Don't move!
尼奥！
Neo!
哦，上帝啊！
Oh, my God!
尼奥！
Neo!
安德森先生!
Mr. Anderson!
不
No!
这不可能
It can't be.
我可想死你了
I've missed you.
都是我脑子里发生的
It's in my mind.
你能听到我说话吗，托马斯？
Can you hear me, Thomas?
跟随我的声音
Follow my voice.
感受你指尖的轻触  它们接触到的是什么？
Feel the tips of your fingers.  What are they touching?
铃响了
The bell.
你听到铃声了吗？
Do you hear the bell?
你还记得发生了什么吗？ 你是怎么来这儿的？
Do you remember what happened? How you got here?
这只猫就叫Deja Vu（似曾相识）
你一定是走来的
You must have walked.
我听到我的猫在外面叫
I heard Deja Vu outside,
一打开门，你就在那里
opened my door, and there you were.
想要好好谈一谈吗？
You feel like you can talk about it?
我们刚开始治疗的时侯，
When we started working together,
你就已经失去了自己
you had lost your capacity
辨别现实与虚构的能力
to discern reality from fiction.
你是在试图跳楼之后来找我的
You came to me after trying to jump off a building.
你说你想要 飞走
You said you wanted to fly away.
那之后我们取得了不少的进展
We have made a lot of progress since then,
但你这次似乎是被特别地刺激到了
but you seem particularly triggered right now.
能告诉我是怎么引起的吗？
Can you tell me how it started?
他发短信给我了
He texted me.
谁？
Who?
墨菲斯
Morpheus.
啊
Ah.
所以，他回来了
So, he's back.
那其实不是他
It wasn't actually him.
他是我为模态写的一个程序
It was a program I coded for a Modal.
而这个“模态”中的墨菲斯
And this "Modal," Morpheus,
过来帮你逃离
came to help you escape
一个叫做矩阵的虚拟现实
from a virtual reality called The Matrix.
我是不是疯了？
Am I crazy?
我们这里不说那个词
We don't use that word in here.
那我该怎么形容呢？
What word should I use?
怎么解释发生在我身上的事情？
What word explains what is happening to me?
我能看看那些短信么？
Can I see the texts?
它们被删除了
They were erased.
如果我们坐上我的车，去你的办公室
If we got in my car and drove to your office,
你觉得我们会在那里发现什么？
what do you think we'd find there?
什么都没有
Nothing.
因为没有发生过袭击
Because there was no attack.
没人被杀
No one was killed.
也没人发短信
No one texted.
是我脑子里制造出来的
My mind made it all up.
这就是我应该说的吗？
Is that what I'm supposed to say?
这就是你相信的吗？
Is that what you believe?
它感觉好真实
It felt real.
那当然了
Of course.
你的雄心壮志就是制作一款游戏，
It was your great ambition to make a game
一款与现实无异的游戏
that was indistinguishable from reality.
为了实现这一目标
To achieve this goal,
你把自己生活中的元素转化成游戏的情节
you converted elements of your life into narrative.
你把自己对商业伙伴的怨气提取出来
Your sublimated anger toward your business partner
让他变成你的死对头
cast him as your nemesis.
一位名叫蒂芙尼的已婚女子
A married woman named Tiffany
成了一段悲剧爱情中的“崔妮蒂”
became the "Trinity" of a doomed romance.
甚至你不喜欢我的猫，所以也把它放进了你的《黑客帝国》里
Even your dislike of my cat made it into your Matrix.
这没有什么不对的
There's nothing wrong with that.
艺术家就是这样做的
It's what artists do.
但是当幻想会危及我们或其他人时
But it becomes a problem when fantasies
它就成了一个问题
endanger us or other people.
我们不希望任何人受到伤害
We don't want anyone to get hurt,
对吧，托马斯？
do we, Thomas?
嗨，托马斯  大家都叫我“蒂芙”
Hi, Thomas.  Everyone calls me "Tiff."
-你是谁？  -我的名字叫崔妮蒂
-Who are you?  -My name is Trinity.
没人能提醒你陷入爱河了
No one can tell you you're in love.
你自己就是知道，从始至终
You just know it, through and through.
刻骨铭心
Balls to bones.
你感觉到了吗？
You feel this?
我永远都不会放手
I'm never letting go.
你必须放下，尼奥
You have to let it all go, Neo.
解放你的意识
Free your mind.
哼
Huh.
貌似不难啊
Looks easy enough.
“解放我的意识”  见鬼去吧
"Free my mind."  Shit.
好吧
Okay.
解放我的意识
Free my mind.
要么起飞……
I fly...
要么坠落
or I fall.
你到底是谁？
Who the hell are you?
你不会记得我的
You won't remember me,
但在很久以前，你改变了我的人生
but a long time ago, you changed my life
当你从另一个楼顶跳下来的时侯
when you leapt off another roof.
coppertop，直译为“电池的铜帽”，在美国是对“金霸王”牌一次性化学电池的简称
此处显然是指被接入矩阵的人形电池们
"coppertop"和"blue pill"都是对深陷矩阵的人的蔑称，就和Harry Potter里的魔法师称普通人为“麻瓜”一个道理
那时侯，我就和其他人肉电池一样
Back then, I was just like any other coppertop,
过着虚假的生活……
pretending my life...
直到我抬头，看见了你
until I looked up and I saw you.
那是一个不同的你，但是我看见了
It was a different you, but I saw
那个真实的你
the real you,
就在你跳楼的……
just a second before...
前一秒
you leapt.
而且你没有掉下去
And you never fell.
就是你黑掉我的模态的吗？
Are you the one that hacked my Modal?
是的
Yeah.
那是裘德打的
That'll be Jude.
他不是你的朋友
He's not your friend.
他是个打手，一个用来控制你的程序
He's a handle, a program used to control you.
他正要来找你
He's on his way here,
还带来了特工
and he's bringing Agents with him.
裘德
Jude.
兄弟，我整晚都在给你打电话
Bro, I've been calling you all night.
我们遇到了一个重大问题
We have a major problemo.
就你一个人吗?
Are you alone?
这个问题有点骚啊，伙计
That's kind of a sexy question, dude.
他们看起来并不像标准的特工
They don't look like typical Agents.
他们现在用了机器人，套着普通人皮肤
They use bots now, skinned as normal people,
Mnemosyne船员（Bugs、Berg、Lexy）在矩阵里都戴着铁链项链，身上有显眼的蓝色衣服/蓝色头发
这么打扮是对奴役者矩阵象征性的挑衅和反抗——他们的同类，那些深陷矩阵的Bluepills丝毫不知自己是奴隶
所以这些觉醒者便通过佩戴奴隶制的标志，时刻铭记自己为奴的经历，象征与受苦的同类站在一起
这就意味着他们无处不在
which means they're everywhere
而你永远不知道该信任谁
and you never know who to trust.
我为什么要信任你？
Why should I trust you?
因为一旦他们打开那扇门，我们就黑不进来了
Because if they open that door, we lose our hack.
他们会抓住我并杀了我
I will be caught and killed
而你立即会被送回
and you will be put right back
他们为你设计的原地重生程序里
on that treadmill they designed for you,
就和上一次他们所做的一样
just like they did the last time
那次你想从楼顶跳下去
you tried to leap your way out.
Matrix wiki解释，那次分析师抹掉了所有楼顶上围观的人的记忆，但就是没想到，吊在外墙上还有一个目击者Bugs
我知道你为什么要让你的模态保持开放状态
I know why you left your Modal open.
你需要别人来解救墨菲斯
You needed someone else to free Morpheus.
正是因为他，我们才能找到你
And it's because of him that we were able to get to you.
我知道这些事情，
I know these things the same way
就像我知道，终有一天我会找到你
that I knew one day I would find you.
而当我找到你的时侯，你已经准备好了
And that when I did, you would be ready for this.
如果你想知道真相，尼奥
If you want the truth, Neo,
你必须跟我来
you're going to have to follow me.
好吧
Okay.
-我们这是在哪儿？  -东京
-Where are we?  -Tokyo.
移动中的传送门会让他们难以追踪我们
moving portal makes it harder to track us.
-希克最擅长这个了 -传送门是安全的
-Seq is the best of them.  -Portal's clean.
读取我们的投影
Reading our shadows.
我不记得有这个
I don't remember this.
我们再也不用跑到电话亭去了
We don't have to run to phone booths anymore, either.
门就在你的右边
Door's on your right.
布置和环境，对吧？
Set and setting, right?
哦，不
Oh, no.
全在于布置
It's all about set
和环境
and setting.
在我们第一次接触失败后
After our first contact went so badly,
我们意识到来自你过去的元素
we thought elements from your past
可能会对你接受现实有帮助
might help ease you into the present.
没有什么比一点点怀旧
Nothing comforts anxiety like
更能缓解焦虑了
a little nostalgia.
这是你游戏中的视频片段
This is footage from your game.
时间总是与我们作对
Time is always against us,
吧啦吧啦
etcetera, etcetera.
没有人能被告知
No one can be told
矩阵到底是什么，吧啦吧啦
what the Matrix is, blah, blah, blah.
你必须亲眼得见才会相信
You gotta see it to believe it.
该起飞了
Time to fly.
等一下
Wait.
如果这是真的
If this is real,
如果我没有失去理智，这是否意味着
if I haven't lost my mind, does that mean
这些都是发生过的？
this happened?
但如果真的发生过……
But if it did...
那我们就已经死了呀
then we died.
很明显不是这样
Obviously not.
为什么机器让你活下来
Why the Machines kept you alive
为什么它们不遗余力地隐藏你
and why they went to such lengths to hide you
这些问题我们都还没找到答案
are questions we don't have answers to.
把我藏起来？
Hide me?
我在一家公司制作了一款叫《黑客帝国》的游戏
I've been at a company making a game called The Matrix.
看起来它们并没有试图去隐瞒什么啊
Doesn't seem like they were trying to hide anything.
我们已经追踪那家公司有好几年了
We've been tracking that company for years.
我们筛选了我们找到的每一个托马斯·安德森
We screened every Thomas Anderson we found.
我们当时还没明白的是
What we didn't understand
它们可以改变你的DSI（数字化自我影像）
was that they could alter your DSI.
培养舱通过一个名为“外表”的反馈系统，
Pods generate your digital self-image
生成你的数字自我影像
through a feedback system called Semblance.
这是你眼中自己的样子
This is how you look to yourself.
它们能通过某种办法，改变你的数字化自我影像循环
Somehow they were able to alter your DSI loop.
这是别人看到你的样子
This is how everyone else sees you.
RSI: Residual self-image 自我形象残留
DSI: Digital self-image 数字自我影像
尼奥和崔尼蒂眼中的自己都是RSI，因为RSI完全取决于心理学自我认同，而其他人眼中的他们都是DSI。
这也是为什么，蒂芙尼的老公看了游戏中崔尼蒂的画面根本get不到意思
二十年了？
Twenty years?
为什么花了二十年时间才找到我？
Why did it take 20 years to find me?
其实花了比这更长的时间
It took a lot longer than that.
现在离你和崔妮蒂飞到机械城
It's been over 60 years since you and Trinity
已经过去六十年了
flew to one of the Machine Cities.
什么？
What?
有太多我们还不知道的事情了
There's so much we don't know.
比如你为什么几乎没有变老
Like why you've barely aged,
或者它们改变了你的DSI多少次
or how many times they've altered your DSI.
但是根据我们已知的
But based on what we do know,
看起来，之所以没有人能找到你
it appears no one found you
是因为你自己就不想被找到
because you didn't want to be found.
-并非如此  -可能并非如此吧
-That's not true.  -Maybe it isn't.
也可能，那些关于你消失的流言
Maybe there's no foundation
译者坚信，墨菲斯提到的这种流言正是真相，因为新矩阵和新IO中的人类越来越善于伪装和自欺
很长一段时间里，尼奥潜意识里害怕被人救出，因为这意味着崔尼蒂可能会受伤害
直到二十年后，他终于选择脱离，才建了模态把自己救出
都毫无根据
to the rumors that you disappeared,
因为你从一开始
because you were working
就在为机器工作了
with the Machines from the beginning.
墨菲斯，别这么说
Morpheus, stop.
我想说的是，现在就是你向我们
All I'm saying is this is the moment
展示什么是真相的时候了
for you to show us what is real.
如果你想逃出来
If you want out,
你就吃下这颗药丸
you'll take this pill.
但如果你觉得自己属于这里
But if you are where you belong,
就吃下这颗然后回去
you can go back to this.
日复一日
Every day.
年复一年，直到永远
Over and over forever.
该死
Fuck.
收紧守卫圈
Keep the loop tight.
赛贝贝需要那个塔的定位
Cybebe needs that tower pin.
我收到信号了  很微弱
I got a signal.  It's faint.
他的培养舱肯定离线了
It's definitely off-grid.
舰长  我追踪到一大堆奇怪的东西
Captain.  I'm tracking a whole lot of weird.
-什么？  -是某种移植程序
-What?  -It's some kind of graft.
托马斯？
Thomas?
哦，上帝啊
Oh, God.
哦，不
Oh, no.
-有人来了  -他们怎么找到我们的？
-We got company.  -How'd they find us?
托马斯，这一切都不是真的
Thomas, none of this is real.
你正处于严重的精神分裂状态
You are in the midst of a serious psychotic break.
-莱克西？ -就快好了
-Lexy?  -Almost there.
托马斯？
Thomas?
托马斯，求你了  这不是闹着玩的
Thomas, please.  This is not a game.
感受我的手
Feel my hand.
这才是真实的事物
This is what is real.
留在我身边
Stay with me.
不  不
No.  No.
留在我身边
Stay with me.
尼奥！
Neo!
墨菲斯！
Morpheus!
快走 快走
Let's go, let's go!
-机器人正在被激活  -是蜂群模式
-Bots are being activated.  -It's a swarm.
快点儿！
Come on!
我在洗手间黑了个出口  要快！
I got a hack in the bathroom.  Hurry!
好的
Yes.
快点儿！
Come on!
希克，在哪儿？
Seq, where?
-那面镜子  -什么？
-That mirror.  -What?
-我们挤不进去  -你们必须挤进去
-We'll never fit.  -You gotta fit,
因为我没别的办法可以离开这辆火车
'cause I don't have another way off this train.
哇 哇 哇
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
想想“透视法”
Think "perspective."
你越接近，它就越大
Closer you are, bigger it gets.
好吧，来吧
Okay, come on.
进去吧
In you go.
崔妮蒂
Trinity.
不！
No!
欢迎回到真实世界
Welcome back to the real world.
崔妮蒂
Trinity.
-医生，他怎么样了？  -他的生命系统
-What's up, Doc?  -His vital systems
得到了精心的维护
have been meticulously maintained,
但情况看起来并不乐观
but it doesn't look good.
-我们要失去他了  -冷启动或许可以救活他
-We're losing him.  -Cold boot could shock him.
动手吧
Do it.
我记得这个
I remember this.
这个构架程序
The Construct.
Construct曾多次出现，它是为加载仿真程序而创建的虚拟空间
墨菲斯第一次为尼奥展示“真实的荒漠”、对战训练、载入枪支都是在这里进行
介于万物
In between everything
和虚无之间
and nothing.
欢迎来到婴儿床
Welcome to the Crib.
我一直被冷藏在船上的网络中...
I've been chilling here in the ship network...
了解着关于你的一切
learning all about you.
还有我自己
And me.
小心点儿  下面的问题是很伤脑的
Careful.  It'll do your head in.
被证明是虚构的记忆 ，就不那么真实了吗？
Are memories turned into fiction any less real?
建立在记忆上的“真实”，或许也不过是“虚构”吗？
Is reality based in memory nothing but fiction?
至于我在这场戏中所扮演的角色，
As to my role in all this, my best guess
我猜你把我编写成了
is that you wrote me
一个代表着两股力量的算法映射
as an algorithmic reflection of two forces
是他们俩促使你成为了救世主：
that helped you become you,
墨菲斯和史密斯特工
Morpheus and Agent Smith.
一个反向编程的
A combo pack
组合文件包，这真是……
of counterprogramming that was...
这么说吧，比疯狂更疯狂的创作
Let's just say, more than a little bit crazy-making.
但它确实有用，因为我们终究来到了这儿
But it worked because here we are.
现在，坏消息是
Now, for the bad news.
你的大脑已经被灌满了
Your brain is hooked on this shit
矩阵这么多年来强制喂给你的垃圾
the Matrix has been force-feeding you for years.
影响很严重
Hooked bad.
你的大脑已经处于严重退行中
You're going through major withdrawals.
医护机器打赌你很难存活下来
Docbots are giving you crap odds for surviving.
但是，你看，他们并不像我这样了解你
But, see, they don't know you like I do.
我完全知道你需要的是什么
I know exactly what you need.
你一定是在开玩笑
You gotta be kidding.
呃-呃
Uh-uh.
不是玩笑
No joke.
这可能会是你重获新生的第一天
Could be this is the first day of the rest of your life.
但如果你想要……
But if you want it...
你就得为之战斗
you gotta fight for it.
不  我已经打够了
No.  I'm done fighting.
是吗？
Are you?
他到底在干什么？
What the hell is he doing?
哦，好吧  他们灌输得真好
Oh, yeah.  They taught you good.
让你相信他们的世界就是你想要的
Made you believe their world was all you deserved.
但你心底里知道那是个谎言
But some part of you knew that was a lie.
你心底里还记得什么是真实
Some part of you remembered what was real.
你并不了解我
You don't know me.
是吗？
No?
唔
Ooh.
我了解你，因为我知道
I know you, because I know
对你来说唯一重要的事情是什么
the only thing that still matters to you.
这就是你为什么来这儿，为什么还在战斗
I know it's why you're here, why you're still fighting
以及为什么你永远不会放弃
and why you will never give up.
来啊，尼奥！
Come on, Neo!
这就是了
This is it.
这是你最后的机会了
This is your last chance.
你得为你该死的性命而战
You gotta fight for your goddamn life
如果你还想见到崔妮蒂的话
if you want to see Trinity again.
来吧，尼奥！ 为她而战！
Come on, Neo!  Fight for her!
-老天呐  -为她而战
-Holy shit.  -Fight for her!
-嗨  -嗨
-Hey.  -Hey.
介不介意我……
Mind if I...
你还好吗？
How are you doing?
如果这个插头确实是真的
If this plug is actually real,
那就意味着，他们把我一生的经历
that means they took my life...
变成了一款电子游戏
and turned it into a video game.
我还好吗？
How am I doing?
我也不知道
I don't know.
我甚至不知道该如何去知道
I don't even know how to know.
事情就是这样，不是吗？
That's it, isn't it?
如果我们不知道什么是真实的……
If we don't know what's real...
我们就无法反抗
we can't resist.
他们拿走了你的故事
They took your story,
拿走了对我这些人来说
something that meant
意义重大的东西
so much to people like me,
并把它变成一些琐碎的事物
and turned it into something trivial.
这就是矩阵所做的
That's what the Matrix does.
它把每一个想法
It weaponizes every idea.
每一个梦想
Every dream.
每一件对我们来说重要的东西，都变成了武器
Everything that's important to us.
还有什么比把真相埋葬在
Where better to bury truth than inside something
电子游戏这类平常事物里更好的办法吗？
as ordinary as a video game?
你这话听起来像是先知说的
That sounds like the Oracle.
我听过很多她的事情
Heard so much about her.
她在我获得自由之前就不在了
She was gone before I was free.
不在了？
Gone?
当这个新版本的矩阵被装载时，
When this new version of the Matrix was uploaded,
有过一次大清洗
there was a purge.
他们承诺了和平，却发动了大清洗
They promised peace and they gave us purge.
不
No.
不，是有过和平
No, there was peace.
是你使和平成为可能，它改变了一切
You made it possible, and it changed everything.
我并没有感觉到改变了什么
Doesn't feel like it changed anything.
矩阵还是一样，甚至更糟
The Matrix is the same or worse.
而我又回到了起点
And I'm back where I started.
感觉就像我所做的一切
It feels like everything I did,
我们所做的一切……
everything we did...
完全没有任何意义
...like none of it mattered.
这一切都是有意义的
All of it mattered.
让我展示给你看
I can show you.
铭牌：Mnemosyne 号
第三代第19号  建于2274年
Mnemosyne是希腊的记忆女神，由此衍生出诸如“助记符”之类的词，即指有助于记忆的东西
值得一提的是，三部曲中，所有战舰铭牌第一行，都与圣经《马可福音》有精妙的对应，暗示着此舰的命运
马可福音 3:19 是耶稣十二使徒名单的末尾，上面写着：“……还有出卖他的加利略人犹大。”
一种解释是：指 Bugs 无视 Niobe 命令（被她形容为“兵变”），去拯救 Neo
这是我的船员
This is my crew.
我们的接线员，希克
Our operator, Seq.
全名是红杉  但大家都叫我希克
Sequoia.  But everybody calls me Seq.
Seq 与"seek"同音，即 查找
它也是一个Linux系统命令，用于生成一定范围内的整数
很高兴认识你
Nice to meet you.
我爸喜欢红杉树
Dad loved redwoods.
当他逃离矩阵时
When he escaped the Matrix
发现这世上已经没有红杉了
and found out they no longer existed,
这几乎要了他的命
it almost killed him.
幸运的是，他遇到了妈妈
Lucky, he met Mom
于是有了我
and here I am.
这是莱克西，伯格和埃尔斯特
This is Lexy, Berg and Ellster.
你们好
Hi.
Roland 即雷神之锤号的舰长，是最后冲进锡安，释放EMP的那艘船
你认识我的祖父，罗兰德舰长
You knew my grandfather, Captain Roland.
罗兰德是你的祖父？
Roland was your grandfather?
他总是笑着，开玩笑说他从来没有相信过你
He always laughed, joking how he never believed in you.
但在私下里，他说
But, in private, he said that
是你第二次解放了他的意识
you freed his mind a second time.
呃，我不是想表示我是你的铁粉
Uh, not to fanboy out here,
但这对我来说是一个重大的时刻
but this is kind of a huge moment for me.
伯格是我们的常驻“尼奥”学家
Berg is our resident Neo-ologist.
一个什么？
A what?
外面有很多像我这样的人
There's a lot of people out there like me
对你的人生故事很着迷
who are a little bit obsessed with your life.
如果不是他的话
I would never have recognized
我永远也认不出你的模态
your Modal if it weren't for him.
等你有时间的话
Whenever you're feeling up for it,
我这儿有几百万个问题呢
I've got, like, a million questions.
我也有  先从它们开始吧
Me too.  Starting with them.
没事儿的
It's okay.
来见见他
Come meet him.
这是赛贝贝
This is Cybebe.
那是八爪鱼
That's Octacles.
那是光体8号
That's Lumin8.
机器现在站在我们这边了吗？
Machines are on our side now?
应该用“合成体”这个词
They are synthients.
与“机器”相比，它们更喜欢用这个词
It's a word they prefer to "Machines."
你与“合成体”的城市的接触
Your contact with the Synthient City
在它们的世界里产生了巨大的影响
had a huge impact on their world.
这就是我要说的
That's what I meant.
你改变了那些
What you changed
大家本以为永远无法改变的东西
that nobody believed could ever be changed.
改变了“我们这边”的含义
The meaning of "our side."
赛贝贝和八爪鱼都冒着生命危险
Cybebe and Octacles risked their lives
把你救了出来
to help get you out.
谢谢你们
Thank you.
但这是为什么呢？
But why?
并非所有东西都寻求被控制
Not all seek to control.
正如并非所有人都希望获得自由一样
Just as not all wish to be free.
那是什么？
What is that?
一种外触变质粒子化编译器  是最新的发明呢
An exomorphic-particle codex.  It's pretty new.
它能让程序进入到这个世界中
It gives programs access to this world.
当然也有范围限制的
Within limits.
限制是被限制者的疆域
Limits are the domain of the limited.
墨菲斯
Morpheus.
谢谢你
Thank you.
这是我的荣幸
It was my honor.
哇哦
Wow.
这东西是怎么运作的？
How does it work?
顺磁振荡
Paramagnetic oscillation.
如果你想要
If you want,
我可以为你下载编译器使用手册
I can download the codex manual for you.
-好啊  -以前随时下载还是挺有趣的
-Sure.  -Downloading used to be fun.
现在啥都有使用手册和诊疗手册了
Now it's all manuals and diagnostics.
我能问它们一些问题吗？
Can I ask them something?
当你拔掉我的插头时，那里是不是还有另一个培养舱？
When you unplugged me, there was another pod?
是的  我们已经分析了数据
Yes.  We've analyzed the data.
那可能是崔妮蒂
It could be Trinity.
那就是她
It's her.
我想我们是该谈谈这件事了
I figured we were going to have this conversation.
听着，你可不是一个典型的同花顺
Look, you were not a typical flush-and-grab.
你被关在那个奇怪的塔里，
You were in this weird tower that Cybebe
赛贝贝从来没去过那里，现在她已经被流放了
had never accessed, and she's now exiled.
我们为你使出了唯一的底牌
We burned our one shot for you.
所以即便那是崔妮蒂，而且她想要获得自由
Even if it were Trinity and she wanted to be free,
我们也不知道该怎么做了
we have no idea how to do it.
是“眼下”还不知道
Yet.
没人相信我们能找到他
Nobody believed we'd ever find him,
但我们还是找到了
but we did.
好吧
Okay.
我们还不知道怎么把她弄出来……至少是眼下不知道
We don't know how to get her out... yet.
舰长，我们快要到安检通道了
Captain, we're approaching security clearance.
我们到了
We're here.
锡安？
Zion?
坐吧
Have a seat.
这是汉诺  我们舰队里最好的飞行员
This is Hanno.  Best pilot in our fleet.
有很多“合成体”
Quite a few synthients
都比我更配得上这一称号
deserve that title before me.
记忆女神号，你已被允许着陆  欢迎回家
Mnemosyne, you are cleared for landing.  Welcome home.
谢谢你 控制中心
Thank you, Control.
嗯……我们要撞上了！
Um, we're about to crash.
将军意识到我们
General realized we were
永远不可能打败哨兵，所以……
never going to beat the Sentinels, so...
我们现在更善于隐藏了
we just got better at hiding from them.
欢迎来到IO
Welcome to IO.
人机共存的新城市IO，有多种解读
最直接的是，字母I O代表“输入输出” <i>Input/Output</i>
另外，IO是01的镜像，暗示人类城IO与机械城01的对应关系，仿佛是历史轮回
（为什么机器的首都叫“01”，参见《黑客帝国 动画版》“第二次文艺复兴”）
历史回顾，全部引用自Matrix Wiki：
尼奥“死后”，墨菲斯当选锡安议会长，但他相信尼奥的牺牲会带来永远的休战，他只对了一半
“建筑师”确实是言而有信，但在机器世界中崛起的新势力推翻了原来建筑师代表的这一派，新势力委派“分析师”接管矩阵
锡安在一次袭击中终被摧毁，但在奈奥比的带领下，幸存的人类在一个隐蔽的洞穴里建立了IO。
机器们陷入了几十年的内战之中，无暇顾及人类的重建，导致IO比锡安更加繁荣
与锡安的严格区分敌我的心态不同，IO是由人类和部分机器共同构建的城市。
奈奥比(已经90岁)领导下的人类，也不再热衷于解救困在矩阵中的意识，而是更关心自己的安全和福利
不过也有少数人被救出，就包括被奈奥比亲手解救的Bugs
哇  天空看起来很真实
Wow.  That looks real.
那是生物天空
Bio-sky.
作用有点像种植灯
Works kind of like grow lights.
比那复杂多了
It's way more complex than that.
它从地壳中抽取水分，给空气加湿
It pulls water from the crust, hydronating the air.
它平衡了生态环境和我们的SRI循环
It balances the ECO and our SRI cycles.
另外……
Plus...
它看起来很漂亮
it is pretty to look at.
那里就不太好看了
As opposed to that.
我猜将军给我们安排了个欢迎会
I guess the general sent us a welcome party.
见鬼了
God damn.
真的是你
It is you.
奈奥比？
Niobe?
多了几条皱纹，少了几颗牙齿
A few more wrinkles and a few less teeth,
但我已足够明智：知道自己其实一无所知
but wise enough to know I don't know anything.
这句话是直接引用自苏格拉底：
As for me, all I know is that I know nothing  至于我，我只知道我一无所知
我真他妈的没想到会这样
I sure as shit never saw this coming.
我也没想到
Neither did I.
我告诉过你他还活着
I told you he was alive.
舰长，你和你的船员被停飞了
Captain, you and your crew have been grounded.
将军，请允许我解释一下
General, if you'd just let me explain.
规定流程是为了保护每个人而制定的
The protocols are put in place for everyone's protection.
我很抱歉  我不能放过这个机会
I'm sorry.  I saw an opportunity
我担心我们会失去他
and I was afraid we'd lose him.
但是将军，大家已经期待他那么久了
But, General, people have been waiting for so long.
我们找到了救世主
We found The One.
Matrix 3中，奈奥比确实亲口说过，自己不相信“救世主”能结束战争
但她接着说，自己信的是尼奥这个人，所以选择把Logos号借给他
我不相信有“救世主”
I don't believe in The One.
从不曾相信
I never did.
不相信？
No?
我也不信
Me neither.
但你曾经
But there was a time
把你的飞船托付给我
when you trusted me with your ship,
因此违背了议会的命令
against the Council's orders.
世界已不同往昔
The world was different then.
我们也不同了
We were different.
去码头报到
Report to the docks.
把记忆女神号擦干净
Scrub down the Mnemosyne.
移交你的准入密码
Transfer your access codes.
你被停职了，舰长
You are done, Captain.
我们需要谈谈
We need to talk.
当第一次传出
When word first came
你可能又出现了的消息时……
that it actually might be you...
我不知道，再见到你那一刻我将是什么感觉
I didn't know how I would feel in this moment.
很高兴见到你
It is nice to see you.
我也很高兴见到你
It's good to see you too.
比多泽弄的脱漆剂好喝多了
A long way from Dozer's paint stripper.
是啊
Yes.
很多东西都变了
A lot has changed.
也许除了你
Except maybe you.
你还记得这个吗？
You remember this?
只有当你拔掉插头之后
It's so easy to forget how much noise
才能意识到，矩阵向你的脑子里
the Matrix pumps into your head
注入了多少噪音
until you unplug.
是啊
Yeah.
其他东西也会制造同样的噪音
Something else makes the same kind of noise.
占据了你的一切，
Takes over every damn thing,
就像矩阵一样
just like the Matrix.
那就是战争
War.
那时，我站在神庙的堡垒后
I stood at the barricade of the Temple.
凝视着哨兵的大军
Staring at the army of Sentinels,
等着它们杀光我们每一个人
waiting for them to kill every one of us.
但接下来，它们离开了
But then, they left.
人们说是你救了我们
They said you saved us.
我并不相信
I didn't believe it.
每天晚上我都会梦到袭击警报
Every night I would dream of attack sirens.
但是之后，
But then,
我醒过来，发现身边是那么的……
I would wake up to this...
安静
silence.
现在，我为此感到羞愧
I'm ashamed of it now.
为自己花了那么长时间才克服悲观，
My pessimism of how long it took me to believe
才去相信，一个没有战争的世界是真的可能的
a world without war was possible.
你给了我这份礼物
You gave me that.
你将它赐予了我们所有人
You gave that gift to us all.
而且这礼物还在继续开花结果
And it is the gift that continues to bear fruit.
过来扶我起来
Come help me get up.
我们去走一走吧
Let's take a walk.
哦！ 真是太美了
Oh!  Beautiful.
这位是弗雷亚，植物学主任
This is Freya, head of botany.
这位是奎利安，我们的首席数字专家
And this is Quillion, our lead digitologist.
我想我们的客人就不用介绍了吧
I presume our guest needs no introduction.
没人能比光更快
Nothing travels faster than light,
除了八卦
except gossip.
欢迎来到花园，尼奥
Welcome to the Garden, Neo.
这是草莓？
A strawberry?
利用矩阵中的数字代码
Using digital code from the Matrix,
我们将其逆向转换为DNA序列
we retro-convert it into DNA sequences.
它们可以在这儿生长吗？
And they grow here?
利用生物天空的光合作用
It's not easy augmenting the genome
来扩增基因组并非易事，但是……
to photosynthesize Bio-sky, but...
我们快做到了
We're getting there.
来啊  尝尝看
Go ahead. Try it.
我们在蓝莓上也取得突破了
We're quite excited about the blueberries.
你还记得我们以前吃的那些垃圾吗？
You remember that shit we used to eat?
那种尝起来像铁锈的糊糊
That slop that tasted like rust.
锡安永远不可能做出这样的东西
Zion could have never made something like this.
为什么？
Why?
因为我们需要像他这样的合成体
Because we needed synthients
和数字智能
and DI like him.
DI 即Digital Intelligence，与"synthients"一样，都是对与人类合作的机器表示尊重的称呼
锡安被困在过去  被困在战争中
Zion was stuck in the past.  Stuck in war.
被困在一个自己建造的“矩阵”中
Stuck in a Matrix of its own.
他们相信人类和机器不能共存
They believed that it had to be us or them.
但这座城市就是我们
This city was built by us
和它们共同建造的
and them.
锡安那里发生了什么？
What happened to Zion?
我一直在等你问这个问题
I've been waiting for you to ask that question.
所有的麻烦都是从机械城开始的
All of the troubles started in the Machine Cities.
发电厂无法生产足够的能源
Power plants were unable to produce enough energy.
没有什么比匮乏更容易滋生暴力了
Nothing can breed violence like scarcity.
那是我们第一次
For the first time,
看到机器相互交战
we saw machines at war with one other.
我们从先知那里得知，一股新势力正在崛起
We got word from the Oracle of a new power rising.
那是我们最后一次听到她的消息
That was the last we heard from her.
墨菲斯
Morpheus.
围城战役胜利后，他被一致推举上
After the siege, he was elected unanimously.
议会的最高席位
High Chair of the Council.
噢，他是多喜欢这事儿啊
Oh, how he loved that.
虽然新势力崛起的消息四下传播
But as rumors of this new power spread,
他却置之不理
he ignored them.
他确信你促成的事情是不会更改的
He was certain what you had done could not be undone.
这种人从来都不会停止相信奇迹
All of these people never stopped believing in miracles,
还有相信你
believing in you.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我怎么知道会发生这种事呢？
How could I know this would happen?
（奇迹是怎么发生的）我们那时候根本没搞明白过
We didn't understand all of it back then.
现在也依然如此
No more than we do now.
我并不想来给你添麻烦，奈奥比
I didn't come here to cause you problems, Niobe,
但是我需要你的帮助
but I need your help.
崔妮蒂还活着
Trinity is alive.
这就带来了另外一个问题
Then there is another question.
它们为什么要让她活着？
Why did they keep her alive?
我无法回答这个问题
I can't answer that.
但只要我还有一线希望能解救她
But if there's a chance I can free her,
我就必须去试试
I have to try.
哪怕这会危及到这座城市的每一个人？
Even if it means endangering everyone in this city?
我很抱歉，尼奥
I'm sorry, Neo.
我不会让锡安的悲剧在IO重演
I won't let what happened to Zion happen to Io.
我希望你够原谅一个老太婆的请求：
I hope you'll forgive an old woman
你跟着谢泼德过去，先去那里
for asking you to go with Sheperd, here,
直到我们能更好地了解
till we have better understanding
到底发生了什么
of what's going on.
我才获得自由，你就要把我关起来？
You're going to imprison me after I just got free?
我知道这看起来不公平
I know it doesn't seem fair,
但岁月对我也不公平啊
but neither does growing old.
你也没听到我抱怨什么吧
But you don't hear me complaining.
抱歉
Sorry.
我以前从没见到过传奇人物
I've never met a legend before.
尼奥
Neo.
谢泼德
Sheperd.
这太疯狂了 你是真实存在的
Crazy.  You're real.
“真实”
"Real."
那个词又来了
There's that word again.
人们经常谈论很多关于过去的事情
People talk a lot about the old days.
关于你，还有那个特工病毒
About you, the viral Agent.
还有锡安围城之战
The siege of Zion.
那时候一切都很简单
Everything was simpler back then.
人们都渴望自由
People wanted to be free.
现在就不一样了
It's different now.
有时候我感觉大家都放弃了
Sometimes it feels like people gave up.
就像是矩阵赢了
Like the Matrix won.
这是你的房间
This is you.
我还想问你一件事儿
And I gotta ask you one thing.
你会飞，那是真的吗？
Is it true you could fly?
酷啊
Cool.
墨菲斯
Morpheus.
哦  将军把你关在长发公主塔里了
Oh.  General stuck you in the Rapunzel tower.
Rapunzel 取自《格林童话》的《长发公主》，情节与本片有一定照应：
公主被女巫抚养并困在高塔里，王子偶遇她，坠入爱河，却被女巫刺瞎双眼（失明的尼奥），迷失荒野。
多年后，王子终于找到了也被放逐的公主，她已经有了孩子。当他们彼此相拥时，她的眼泪立刻治好了他的眼睛，从此幸福生活
从好的方面讲，至少风景还不错
On the upside, it's a nice view.
巴格斯和其他人怎么样了？
What happened to Bugs and the others?
他们应该在用牙刷擦洗
They're supposed to be sterilizing the Mnemosyne
-记忆女神号呢  -“应该”？
-with a toothbrush.  -"Supposed to be"?
好吧，我可以告诉你他们在时刻待命呢
Well, I could tell you that they're standing by,
就等着你做出选择
waiting for you to make the choice
要么继续温顺地被监禁
to remain meekly incarcerated
要么冲出这里，去找崔妮蒂
or bust the hell out of here and go and find Trinity.
但这其实算不上“选择”
But that ain't a choice.
将军，我们该怎么办？
General, what should we do?
巴格斯向来保持着独立意识，
Bugs has the same independence of mind
从你给她自由的那一天起就没变过
she had the day you freed her.
这不是什么独立思想
This is not independence of mind.
这是叛变
It's mutiny.
拜托了，比比
Come on, 'Be.
我知道你有多讨厌把他关起来
I know how much you hated locking him up.
就像我知道你内心深处
Just like I know there's a part of you
也为他的离开松了一口气
That's relieved now, that he's gone.
我们为保护IO的安全付出了这么多努力
We've worked so hard to keep Io safe.
这让我感到害怕
This scares me.
她在那儿！
That's her.
在桥上
On the bridge.
找到她了
Got her.
“外表”程序的工作机制真恶心
It's sick how the Semblance works.
你只能看到几个真实自我的闪现，但...
You see flashes of the real her, but...
从代码角度看……
the way she reads...
她是个纯纯的蓝药丸
Code-wise, she's pure bluepill.
这是个麻烦的问题，尼奥，但我必须得问
This is a tough question, Neo, but it has to be asked.
如果她在矩阵里活得很开心呢？
What if she's happy where she is?
我当时的代码看起来怎样？
How did I read?
和她一模一样
Exactly like her.
上升到广播深度
Take us to broadcast depth.
谢谢你帮助我
Thank you for helping me.
我们中的大多数是因为你才能来到这儿
Most of us are here because of you.
我也得承认
I also admit our only chance
我们离开将军那狗窝的唯一机会
to get out of the general's doghouse
就是帮你找回魔力
is for you to find your mojo.
那如果我变不回从前的我呢？
What if I can't be what I once was?
那我们就完蛋了
Then we're all fucked.
两分钟
Two minutes.
两分钟后开始广播
Two minutes to broadcast.
我找个酒店房间带你们穿过去
I slipped you in through a hotel room.
应该会安全些
Should be safe.
传送门打开了
Portal's open.
我最近只能把你们送到她车库附近的仓库了
Closest I could get you is the warehouse near her garage.
这儿整个区域充满了机器人
Whole zone's crawling with bots.
我们走吧
Let's go.
那么，你觉得他怎么样？
So, what do you think of him?
起初我挺担心的，他年纪有点大了
I was kinda worried at first because he's so much older.
那胡子，那头发…… 天呐
The beard, the hair...  Oh.
-不，其实我就好这口  -你个白痴
-No, totally works for me.  -You idiot.
我指的是“就剩他一个儿 ”那件事儿
I mean "The One" thing.
你知道，和他一条船上的人都死了
You know, everyone that shipped with him died.
哦，没错  他肯定会害死我们所有人
Oh, yeah.  He's gonna get us all killed, for sure.
这可能是导演的自嘲，所以后面的大战中，故意让一个人都没死， 贯彻了“情节镜像”的手法
总是那么好预测
Predictable as ever.
史密斯
Smith.
史密斯？ 是指“那个”史密斯吗？
Smith?  As in, "the" Smith?
这真是太疯狂了
This is so insane.
有太多关于他俩的理论了
There's so many theories about the two of them
而他们现在就站在那儿
and they're standing right there.
这个代码太奇怪了！
This code is freaky!
他像是个特工，但又不是
He's like an Agent, but not.
让我们诉诸理性吧
An appeal to reason.
你是怎么找到我们的？
How did you find us?
你一点也不珍惜我们的关系
You never appreciated our relationship.
一点也不像分析师那样
Not like The Analyst.
-谁？ -我的心理医生
-The what?  -My doctor.
他把我们的羁绊变成了锁链
He used our bond and turned it into a chain.
你一眼就看出来了吧？
It's so obvious once you see it, right?
但是整个修改了的代码更新真让我大吃一惊
But this whole altered-code update really blew my mind.
我至今不知道他是怎么做到的
I still don't know how he did it.
你，成了一个秃顶的呆子
You, as a balding nerd.
滑稽可笑
Hilarious.
而我呢...
And me...
甚至更完美了
even more perfect.
也许这双锐利的眼睛有点蓝过头了
Maybe a little too far on the piercing blue eyes.
但你觉得呢？
What do you think?
你想要干什么，史密斯？
What do you want, Smith?
我也有过那样的梦，汤姆
I have such dreams, Tom.
伟大的梦想
Big dreams.
好吧，其实大部分只是幻想着极端暴力的复仇
Well, mostly just extremely violent revenge fantasies,
但是，为了去追求我的梦想
but in order for me to pursue mine,
我得劝阻你放弃追求你的
I need to dissuade you from pursuing yours.
嗯  听起来我们有点冲突啊
Hmm.  Sounds like conflict.
不可避免吗？
Inevitable?
不一定非要这样
Doesn't have to be.
你所要做的就是远离矩阵
All you have to do is stay out of the Matrix,
让我来收拾那个心理医生
and leave the good doctor to me.
医生可以给你  我来这儿是为了崔妮蒂
You can have him.  I'm here for Trinity.
这就是问题所在，汤姆
That's the trouble, Tom.
他知道你会来，就像我一样
He knew you'd come, just like I did.
相信我
Trust me.
你还没准备好对付他
You're not ready for him.
舰长，我从低频信号中发现了一些传送门
Captain, I'm reading portals from the lower frequencies.
我不会再让他把皮带拴在我的脖子上了
I won't have his leash on my neck again.
我找到了你的一些老熟人
I found some old acquaintances of yours.
巴格斯！
Bugs!
流亡者
Exiles.
我还以为他们都被清除了
I thought they were all purged.
你
You?
哦吼吼！
Oh!
就是你！
It is you!
这么多年了 我简直不敢相信
All these years.  I can't believe it.
哦，上帝啊
Oh, God.
你偷走了我的生活！
You stole my life!
史密斯和梅罗纹加的联盟，可能代表着新矩阵三股势力中的一股——回退派
而分析师和萨蒂，分别代表了建制派和合作革新派
他们试图杀掉或劝说尼奥离开，是因为知道，一旦没了4.0版矩阵的首席设计师尼奥，按流程矩阵应回退到3.0版本
在旧版矩阵中，他们显然都更有权势，这便是”要找回我们过去的生活，你就得去死“的根源
梅罗想说的是
What the Merv is trying to say,
他们的处境和我的有点像
is that their situation is a little bit like mine.
要找回他们过去的生活，你就得去死
To have their lives back, yours has to end.
干掉他！
Kill him!
你毁掉了
You ruined
每一件称我心意的事！
every suck-my-silky-ass thing!
我们曾经那么优雅
We had grace.
我们也很有格调！
We had style!
我们还能面对面交谈！
We had conversation!
而不是这种逼逼逼逼……（模仿手机屏幕打字的声音）
Not this...
译者吐槽：这里不应理解为模仿开枪的声音——毕竟法国人养了那么多打手，就是为了“一上来就动手动脚”
以前的艺术、电影、书籍都更好！
Art, films, books were all better!
原创性至上！
Originality mattered!
现在你给了我们“脸书-扎克-吸屌伯格”
You gave us Face-Zucker-suck
还有“日我-气候变暖-维基屎科”
and Cock-me-climatey-Wiki-piss-and-shit!
我还是会功夫的
I still know kung fu.
尼奥！
Neo!
就和以前一样
Just like old times.
尼奥
Neo.
我一直在思考我们的关系，汤姆
I've been thinking about us, Tom.
看看吧，事物的表象和本质是那么的二元对立
Look how binary is the form, the nature of things.
1和0
Ones and zeros.
光明与黑暗
Light and dark.
选择与和没得选
Choice and its absence.
安德森与史密斯
Anderson and Smith.
你已经失去了一些东西，汤姆
You've lost something, Tom.
你已经不是过去的你了
You're not what you used to be.
这是事实
It's true.
-不错嘛  -谢谢
-Nice one.  -Thanks.
加油 尼奥
Come on, Neo.
舰长  你没事儿吧？
Captain.  You okay?
是的  尼奥在哪儿？
Yeah.  Where's Neo?
史密斯要杀了他
Smith is killing him.
在哪儿？
Where?
对此我感到很难过，汤姆
I feel bad about this, Tom.
毕竟，是你让我获得了自由
After all, you are the one who set me free...
再一次地
again.
所以，你比任何人都更能理解，
So, you, more than anyone,
我为什么不能回头了
understands why I can't go back.
你早该听我的话的
You should have listened to me.
现在你再也见不到她了
Now you'll never see her again.
那是什么？
What was that?
那是尼奥
That was Neo.
魔法觉醒了
Mojo rising.
你没事儿吧？
You all right?
还好
Yeah.
这个会引发连锁反应的
It's gonna trigger a response.
我已经准备了多个出口
I got multiple exits ready.
我们还没完呢！
This is not over yet!
续集还有衍生品的特许经营权问题！
Our sequel franchise spinoff!
我们得走了
We should go.
我不能
I can't.
我还得和她谈谈
I have to talk to her.
尼奥，那些流亡者比你还古老
Neo, those Exiles were older than you,
而我们差点对付不了他们
and we barely handled them.
你真的要现在和她聊吗？
You really wanna do this now?
我是说...
I mean...
你看起来糟透了
you look like shit.
哦，天呐  怎么了？ 发生什么了？
Oh, my God.  What?  What happened?
意外事故
An accident.
库什！ 快叫医生
Kush!  Call a doctor.
没关系的
It's fine.
我没多少时间了
I don't have a lot of time.
我不确定是否还能再见到你
I wasn't sure I'd see you again.
我们上次聊完后，我意识到……
After we spoke, I realized...
我的生活不是真正的生活
my life wasn't a life.
某种程度上说，我想我是放弃了
At some point, I think I gave up
去寻找真实的东西
searching for something real.
等等
Wait.
我身上发生了一些事
Something happened.
我去咖啡店找过你
I looked for you at the coffee shop.
我开始怀疑，你是不是我想象出来的
I began to wonder if I imagined you.
然后昨晚我做了一个梦
And then last night I had a dream.
在梦中，你被警察包围
In the dream, you were surrounded by police,
然后他们开始追捕我们
then they started chasing us.
-我们？  -你和我一起骑着我的摩托车
-Us?  -You were on my bike with me.
结局如何？
How did it end?
不太好
Not good.
我曾做过不只是梦的梦
I've had dreams that weren't just dreams.
你是说一个梦成真了？
You mean a dream that came true?
终于，我们可以像成年人一样交谈了
Finally, we can talk like adults.
我讨厌撒谎  真的  它让我筋疲力尽
I hate lying.  I do.  It exhausts me.
蒂芙和我一直在等你……
Tiff and I have been waiting for you...
就像是，等了一辈子
like, forever.
似曾相识，对吧？
Deja vu, right?
哦，没用的  你赢不了时间的
Oh, no use.  You can't beat time.
这种倒带的速度比你眨个眼都快
This rewind is happening faster than you can blink.
是你给了我这个创意
You gave me the idea.
请允许我用一个词来概括我们的目标
Allow me to sum up our goal in a single word.
这其实是引用了头脑风暴中，那个死胖子裘德的原话
暗示了分析师可以深度操控手下的bots的言行
“子弹时间”
"Bullet time."
我知道  有点讽刺啊
I know.  Kind of ironic,
用定义了你的能力来控制你
using the power that defined you to control you.
“定义”一词，指的是“子弹时间”是救世主 最具代表性的超能力
我一直那么密切地关注着你
I kept such a close eye on you
但你还是给自己找到了出路
and still you found a way out.
小机灵鬼儿啊，利用那个模态
Clever monkey, using that Modal.
可以说我是个乐天派
Call me an optimist,
但本来这一切都是那么天衣无缝的
but this could all be for the best.
这次的皮肤看起来还不错啊
The skin's not looking too bad this time.
我知道有些话你是不会想听的
I know some of this will be difficult for you to hear,
在你经历了这一切之后，
after everything you went through.
那么多的苦难和折磨……
All that pain and suffering,
结果只是发现，自己都“死了”，矩阵世界还是没有终结
only to learn the world doesn't end when you do.
意外吧
Surprise.
你死的时候我在场
I was there when you died.
我对自己说
I said to myself,
"这真是一个异常中的异常啊"
"Here is the anomaly of anomalies."
anomaly可以特指"The One"，也可以模糊处理为异常状况
这话指的是尼奥与史密斯湮灭时，竟然从身体中发出了大量的能量/光
这是个多么难得的机会啊
What an extraordinary opportunity.
首先，我得说服管理层
First, I had to convince the Suits
经译者反复查证，the suits 绝对不是指上一任的“建筑师”
让我重建你们两个
to let me rebuild the two of you.
为什么还有她？ 等下就说到
Why her?  Getting there.
别担心，她听不到我说话
And don't worry, she can't hear me.
复活你们俩的花费高得离谱
Resurrecting you both was crazy expensive.
就像翻修旧房子一样
Like renovating a house.
花了两倍的时间，两倍的费用
Took twice as long, cost twice as much.
我本以为你会很高兴再活一次
I thought you'd be happy to be alive again.
大错特错
So wrong.
你知道希望和绝望用代码表示几乎是一样的吗？
Did you know hope and despair are nearly identical in code?
我们努力了好几年
We worked for years,
试图激活你的源代码
trying to activate your source code.
我正准备要放弃的时候 我意识到...
I was about to give up, when I realized...
崔妮蒂
Trinity.
从来不能只靠你一个人
...it was never just you.
你们中的任何一个，独自都没有任何特殊的价值
Alone, neither of you is of any particular value.
就像酸和碱，
Like acids and bases,
只要混在一起，你们就会变得危险
you're dangerous when mixed together.
每次把你们俩弄在一起的模拟实验……
Every sim where you two bonded...
这么说吧，都会发生严重后果
Let's just say bad things happened.
尼奥
Neo!
然而，只要我设法让你们离得很近
However, as long as I managed to keep you close,
但又不能太近
but not too close,
就会有一些不可思议的事情发生
I discovered something incredible.
这么说吧，我的前任（即建筑师）热衷于精确
Now, my predecessor loved precision.
他的矩阵里全是严苛的运算和等式
His Matrix was all fussy facts and equations.
他憎恨人类的思想
He hated the human mind.
所以他从来就没有费心去认识到
So he never bothered to realize
你们根本就不在乎事实
that you don't give a shit about facts.
你们只在乎虚构
It's all about fiction.
唯一重要的东西是在这里
The only world that matters is the one in here.
你们人类会相信最疯狂的东西
And you people believe the craziest shit.
为什么？
Why?
是什么验证并使得 你们的虚构成了真？
What validates and makes your fictions real?
是感受
Feelings.
译者吐槽：Feelings不应被译作“情感”，因为它指的是人与外界环境的交互体验，是它塑造了”真实“
新矩阵施加给了尼奥噩梦和可望不可得的爱情，还用”手指感受到的才是真实“蒙蔽他
“希望和绝望用代码表示几乎一样”，都会使矩阵感觉越来越真实，分析师看透了人性
让我演示一下
Allow me.
库什是我的一个打手
Kush, here, is one of my handlers.
他们无处不在
They're everywhere.
把特工程序克隆到人肉电池身上，真是一件苦差事
Such a pain, cloning Agents over a coppertop.
相比之下让人口饱和的差事，就要简单的多
Far more effective just to saturate a population.
而且，奖赏就是，蜂群模式还是种变态的乐趣呢
And, bonus, swarm mode is sick fun.
哇哦！干得好
Ooh!  Nicely done.
你有没有想过为什么你会做噩梦？
You ever wonder why you have nightmares?
为什么你自己的大脑要折磨你？
Why your own brain tortures you?
这实际上是我们在让你的产出最大化
It's actually us, maximizing your output.
它就是这么运作的
It works just like this.
”哦，不！ 你能阻止子弹吗？“
Oh, no!  Can you stop the bullet?
“要是你能再快一点儿就好了”
If only you could move faster.
感受就是这样
Here's the thing about feelings.
它们比事实容易控制得太多
They're so much easier to control than facts.
结果，在我的矩阵里，
Turns out, in my Matrix,
我们越是折磨你，就越能操纵你
the worse we treat you, the more we manipulate you,
你产生的能量就越多
the more energy you produce.
真是太疯狂了
It's nuts.
我一直在不断刷新产能记录
I've been setting productivity records
自从我接手以来年年如此
every year since I took over.
而且，最好的地方就是，毫无反抗
And, the best part, zero resistance.
人们呆在自己的培养舱里
People stay in their pods,
比屎里打滚的猪还快乐
happier than pigs in shit.
这一切的关键是什么呢？
The key to it all?
是你
You.
还有她
And her.
静静地渴望着你得不到的东西
Quietly yearning for what you don't have,
同时又害怕失去你所拥有的
while dreading losing what you do.
对你们种族99.9%的人来说，
For 99.9% of your race,
这就是对“真实”的定义——
that is the definition of reality.
欲望与恐惧，宝贝儿
Desire and fear, baby.
人类就想要这个，我们就给了他们，对吧？
Just give the people what they want, right?
她是你唯一的归宿了，托马斯
She's the only home you have, Thomas.
在可怕的事情发生之前，回家吧
Come home before something terrible happens.
-巴格斯！  -我听到他了
-Bugs!  -I hear him.
崔妮蒂！
Trinity!
-你不该这样叫我  -我很抱歉
-You shouldn't call me that.  -I'm sorry.
我得走了
I have to go.
但我还会回来的
But I'll be back.
尼奥！ 该走了
Neo!  Time to go.
-哨兵？ -比那更糟
-Sentinels?  -Worse.
将军命令我
General ordered me
照看好这艘船
to look after the ship.
所以你跟踪了我们？
So you shadowed us?
看看你的远程扫描吧
Check your long-range scans.
乌贼正在搜寻这一区域
Squids are combing this area.
他说的没错
He's right.
你要么呆在这里等死
You can stay here and die,
要么回去面对军事法庭
or come back and face a court-martial.
你管这叫“选择”？
And you call that a choice?
谢泼德真该把你们留给乌贼的
Sheperd should have left you to the Squids.
我他妈的太老了，没法再坐着听无聊的审判
I'm too damn old to sit through some boring-ass trial.
奈奥比，别怪巴格斯
Niobe, don't blame Bugs.
闭上你的嘴
Do shut your mouth.
要称呼我“将军”
Do address me as General.
也不要替我的前舰长行使职权
And do not rob my ex-captain of her agency,
她已经用自己特有的
which she exercised with her own
短视的愚蠢行使了这一权利
particular brand of shortsighted stupidity.
目光短浅？
Shortsighted?
你更关心种植水果，而不是解放意识
You care more about growing fruit than freeing minds.
我不想再跟你争论这些
We are not going to have this argument again.
这不是争论  这是事实
It's not an argument.  It's a fact.
你放弃了人们
You gave up on people.
我告诉你我要放弃什么
I tell you what I'm going to give up on
那就是你！
and it's you!
谢泼德，带她从我眼前滚开
Sheperd, get her out of my sight!
将军……
General...
放下武器！
Disarm!
库加库是我的朋友
Kujaku's a friend.
"Kujaku" 是日语 即“孔雀”
你好啊，朋友
Hello, friend.
好的
Okay.
他？
Him?
将军
General.
谢谢你来见我
Thank you for seeing me.
我想如果有人
I figured if there was anyone
能理清这些乱七八糟的事情
who could make sense of this mess,
那就只有你了
it would be you.
你好，尼奥
Hello, Neo.
我认识你
I know you.
我一直密切关注着你
I tried to keep my eye on you.
为什么？
Why?
我们很久以前就认识了
We met a long time ago.
早上好
Good morning.
萨蒂
Sati.
我父亲知道我们还会再见面的
My father knew we'd meet again,
尽管他希望再见面是在一个更美好的环境下
though he would have wished for happier circumstances.
他在你的不幸遭遇中，无意扮演的角色
His inadvertent role in what happened to you
是他这辈子最后悔的事了
was the greatest regret of his life.
我听不明白
I don't understand.
我的父亲是异常处理部的
My father was the chief engineer
首席工程师
at the Anomaleum.
什么部？
The what?
我父亲设计的复活仓
My father designed the resurrection pods
被用来囚禁尼奥和崔尼蒂
where Neo and Trinity were imprisoned.
抱歉插话
I'm sorry.
你早就知道他身上发生的事情？
You knew what happened to him?
你知道他和崔妮蒂都还活着...
You knew that he and Trinity both were alive...
却没有告诉我？
and you didn't tell me?
有好几次我也质疑自己的决定，奈奥比
There were times I doubted my decision, Niobe.
但IO需要你
But Io needed you.
这座城市需要建起
This city needed to be built
是为了你的人民，还有我的人民
for your people as well as mine.
如果我把一切都告诉你
If I would have told you everything,
你就会很难做出选择
you would have had a very difficult choice to make.
我的朋友
My friends
Matrix 3中，奈奥比见过先知，先知说尼奥会需要她的帮助，而且那个时候，奈奥比必须自己选择是否帮助他
因此，奈奥比此处的突然转变，是在弥补多年前未能去做的选择——再次帮助尼奥
请让我自己做选择
let me make my own choices.
如果这是一个错误
If it was a mistake,
我向你表示最深切的歉意
you have my deepest apologies.
你为什么现在过来？
Why are you here now?
尼奥的逃脱破坏了矩阵的稳定
Neo's escape has destabilized the Matrix.
现在异常处理部只能
The Anomaleum draws its current
从崔妮蒂那里汲取能量
from Trinity alone now.
故障保险机制已经被触发，
A fail-safe has been triggered to reset
这会让矩阵回退到早期的版本
the Matrix back to the previous version.
但分析师暂停了重置
But The Analyst halted the reset.
他让上级们相信
He's convinced the authorities
你很快就会自愿回来的
that you will soon return voluntarily.
他为什么会这么说？
And why would he say that?
因为如果我不回去的话，他就会杀了崔妮蒂
Because if I don't go back, he'll kill Trinity.
面对着要么返回培养舱
Faced with returning to your pod
要么再次承受崔妮蒂的死亡
or enduring Trinity's death again.
你会怎么选择，尼奥？
What would you choose, Neo?
我会选择回去
I'll go back.
好吧，分析师很了解你
Well, The Analyst knows you well,
但太了解反而会让他大意
but that knowledge has made him incautious.
在你脱逃之后
After you escaped,
他本该接受损失并转移崔妮蒂
he should have accepted his losses and devacuated Trinity.
但那样就不会有这样一个千载难逢的机会
But that would have prevented this extraordinary opportunity
摆在我们面前了
that now exists before us.
几个小时以前
A few hours ago,
没有人能够说服我
no one would have been able to convince me
让我站到这里，去试图下达一个，
that I would be standing here, trying to explain a mission
如此疯狂的任务
as crazy as this one.
你在做什么？
What are you doing?
-志愿前往  -错了
-Volunteering.  -Oh, no.
你是那个，我要下命令去让你行动的舰长
You are the one captain that I am ordering to go.
那你现在用不着下命令了，将军
Now you don't have to order me, General,
因为我是志愿的
'cause I'm volunteering.
我还需要两个人
I need two more.
你们都疯了吗？
Are you out of your minds?
你们甚至都不了解是什么任务
You don't even know what it is.
将军，可我们了解你
General, we know you.
如果你说这很重要
If you say this is important,
我们没有人会选择呆在家里
none of us is choosing to stay home.
谢谢你们
Thank you.
振作起来，祝你好运
Knuckle up, and good luck.
崔妮蒂被困在异常处理部
Trinity is held in the Anomaleum,
就在这个输电塔里
which is in this transmission tower.
之前用来营救尼奥的通道已被封锁
The passages used to rescue Neo are now sealed
一大群哨兵正在塔里巡逻
and a legion of Sentinels patrols the tower.
所以，潜伏是首要的
So, stealth will be paramount.
只要我们不触发警报
As long as we raise no alarms,
任务的第一部分应该是最简单的
this first part of the mission should be the easiest.
你的意思是穿过胚胎种植场
You mean crossing the Fetus Fields,
偷偷穿过整个发电厂
sneaking across an entire power plant,
攀登一座两公里高的塔
climbing a two-kilometer tower
还是在成千上万的哨兵把守的情况下？
guarded by thousands of Sentinels?
这就是最简单的部分？
That's the easy part?
确实如此
Exactly so.
因为我们所要做的就只是
Because all we have to do is convince someone
说服那个每天都干这事儿的“人”
who does this every day
带我们其中的一个过去
to take one of us along.
在异常处理部下面50米处
Fifty meters below the Anomaleum
是一层羊膜过滤器
is a stratum of amniotic filters.
它的边上隐藏着一个小的六边形通风口
Hidden along this edge is a small hexagonal vent.
这个通风口将空气送入微粒调节器
This vent feeds the air intake into the corpuscular modifier,
而微粒调节器是用来为尼奥的舱中的生物凝胶充氧的
which oxygenates the bio-gel used in Neo's pod.
我明白了
I get it.
我的微粒外晶可以从尼奥的旧脐带里滑动
The exomorph slinkies up Neo's old umbilicus.
这能出什么问题呢？
What could go wrong?
一旦进入
Once inside,
墨菲斯将使用系统操作平台
Morpheus will use the System Operator
打开破碎管线，使浸渍器脱离
to open the devacuator line and disengage the macerators.
为了在拔掉崔妮蒂身上的插头时
In order to unplug Trinity's body,
继续保持她与矩阵的连接
while her mind still remains connected to the Matrix,
我需要另一个人脑
I'm gonna need a second human brain
来构建旁路
to implement the bypass.
因为尼奥必须和分析师在一起
And since Neo must be with The Analyst,
那么附近唯一能用的大脑
the only available mind that's a near-enough match
就是你的
is yours.
明白
Figures.
谢了，赛贝贝
Thanks, Cybebe.
崔妮蒂还需要吃红色药丸吗？
Does Trinity still have to take the red pill?
既然库加库和我会
Since Kujaku and I are transferring
把她的意识转移到船上
her consciousness onto the ship,
严格来说它并不是必需的
it's not strictly necessary.
但重要的是，这得由她自己选择
But what matters is that this is her choice.
抽取一个困惑或犹疑的意识，
Extracting a confused or an uncertain mind will,
只会杀死她
in all probability, kill her.
但即便她想要自由
But even if it is what she wants,
分析师难道不会派哨兵来阻止你吗？
won't The Analyst just order the Sentinels to stop you?
他会的
He will.
但如果我的计划奏效，那就无关紧要了
But if my plan works, it won't matter.
为什么？
Why?
因为我们已经跑了
Because we'll already be gone.
如果有人那么费心去设计计划
Somebody thinks this hard about a plan,
肯定是有原因的
there has to be a reason why.
当我父亲意识到
When my father realized
异常处理部要被用来做什么时
how the Anomaleum was going to be used,
他将设计偷偷转交给了我
he covertly transferred the designs to me.
分析师发现了他的背叛
The Analyst discovered his betrayal
就清除了我的父母
and had my parents purged.
如果不是有库加库，我也会被杀害的
I would have been murdered too if it wasn't for Kujaku.
我没有一天不为他们悲伤
Not a day goes by that I don't grieve them.
我为这一天的到来祈祷了很久了
I've been praying for this day for a very long time.
我们马上要开始广播了
We're coming up on broadcast.
我想你应该知道，我在这里都是因为她
I thought you should know that I'm here because of her.
我想要的就是像崔妮蒂那样无所畏惧
All I ever wanted was to be as fearless as Trinity.
但当我看到她在车库里的反应之后，我...
But I saw how she reacted in the garage, and I...
你在想我是不是错了
You're wondering if I'm wrong.
如果我们已经太迟了呢？
What if we're too late?
如果她再也不是崔妮蒂了呢？
What if she's not Trinity anymore?
我以前从未相信自己是救世主
I never believed I was The One.
但她相信
But she did.
她相信我
She believed in me.
现在轮到我相信她了
It's my turn to believe in her.
现在是最要命的时候
This is where it gets tricky.
你做过这样的操作吗？
Have you ever done an operation like this?
还没有
Not yet.
我们开始吧
Here we go.
欢迎回家
Welcome home.
我只是想和她谈谈
All I want is to talk to her.
你是说和蒂芙吗？
Do you mean Tiff?
回来吧，你可以经常找她聊个够
Come back, and you can talk to her as often as you like.
我的意思是，帅气的查德
I mean, handsome Chad
可能会对此有点儿意见
may have something to say about it.
如果她告诉我，这一切都是她想要的
If she tells me this is what she wants,
你赢
you win.
真的吗？
Really?
但如果她想要的是我
But if she wants me,
那么你就放我们自由离开吧
then you'll let us go free.
我为什么要做这种蠢事儿？
And why would I do something as stupid as that?
现在，我在一艘满载的船上，如果你强行带走我
Right now, I'm on a ship full of people who will unplug me
他们就会拔掉我的插头
before they'll let you take me back.
如果你还想要这个版本的矩阵
If you want this Matrix,
这是你唯一的机会了
this is your only chance.
但我怎么知道，如果我赢了他们会不会也拔掉你的插头呢？
But how do I know they won't unplug you anyway?
就像我不知道，你会不会让我们离开这里一样
Same way I know you'll let us walk out of here.
好吧
Okay.
我喜欢测试
I like tests.
我们让蒂芙来决定吧
We'll let Tiff decide.
搞定了
That's it.
旁路准备好了
Bypass is ready.
现在要做什么？
Now what?
我们得等着
We wait.
我们大老远跑来却把她留在这里
Doesn't it seem crazy to come all this way
难道不是疯了吗？
and leave her here?
我们必须遵从她的决定
We must abide by her decision.
如果她拒绝
And if she says no,
尼奥会怎样？
what happens to Neo?
这一次
At this time,
尼奥一生中最重要的选择，
the most important choice of Neo's life
不是由他来决定的
is not his to make.
我梦到了这一幕
I saw this in my dream.
如果我是先知，也许我还能解释一下
If I was the Oracle, maybe I could explain it.
先知
The Oracle.
你游戏里的那个？
From your game?
它不是个游戏
It's not a game.
哦，天呐
Oh, God.
你离开后，我回到家里
After you left, I went home
我玩了你的游戏
and I played it.
我一直在想
I kept thinking,
为什么这个故事就像是一段回忆？
why does this story feel like a memory?
在我内心深处某个地方
There's a part of me
好像我已经等了你一辈子了
that feels like I have been waiting my whole life for you.
内心深处就像是在说
And that part is like,
“你怎么花了这么久才找到我？”
"What the hell took you so long?"
这个我很难去回答
I don't have an easy answer.
也许是我害怕这个
Maybe I was afraid of this.
害怕可能会发生的事情
Afraid of what might happen.
害怕伤害我唯一的挚爱
Afraid of hurting the only person I ever loved.
我真希望我是你所认为的那个人
I wish I was who you think I am.
但是看看我
But look at me.
我没法成为她
I can't be her.
-妈妈  -妈妈 快点儿
-Mom!  -Mom!  Come on.
-妈妈  -是凯莉
-Mom!  -It's Callie.
这是真实的吗？
Is this real?
你得跟我们走一趟
You have to come with us.
快点儿，我们得走了
Come on, we gotta go.
蒂芙，嘿  我不知道这儿发生了什么
Tiff, hey.  Don't know what's going on here,
但真高兴能找到你
but I'm glad we found you.
-她被车撞了！ -我知道，简直是疯了
-She got hit by a car!  -I know, it's crazy.
她当时追着你过来
She was chasing after you.
他们在给她的胳膊打石膏  我们得走了
They're casting her arm.  We gotta go.
医生说她会没事儿的
Doctor said she's gonna be fine.
你得和我们一起去医院
You have to come with us to the hospital.
太迟了
It's too late.
我能理解
I understand.
-蒂夫，来吧，我们走  -来吧
-Tiff, come on, let's go.  -Come on.
发生了什么？
What's happening?
尼奥错了
Neo was wrong.
蒂芙尼
Tiffany.
蒂芙尼，你必须跟我们走
Tiffany, you have to come with us.
蒂芙尼！
Tiffany!
我希望你别他妈的再这么叫我了
I wish you would fucking stop calling me that.
我讨厌那个名字
I hate that name.
我的名字是崔妮蒂
My name is Trinity
你最好把手从我身上拿开
and you better take your hands off of me.
尼奥！
Neo!
崔妮蒂！
Trinity!
哦，糟糕
Oh, shit.
现在把她弄出来  把她弄出来！
Get her out.  Get her out!
哎呀呀，真是一团糟
Aye-yi-yi, what a mess.
这是我的错  我就不该答应
I own that mistake.  Shouldn't have pressed.
女人以前是那么好控制
Women used to be so easy to control.
你知道，我不可能放你们两个自由的
You know there's no way I can let you two go free.
绝不可能
Cannot happen.
所以，我想这一切又都是似曾相识了
So, I guess it's deja vu all over again.
她会死
She dies
这都是你的错
and it's all your fault.
谎言，谎言，一个接一个谎言
Lies, lies and more lies.
史密斯？
Smith?
这个世界都变成什么样子了？
What has the world come to
连程序都不能被信任了
when you can't even trust a program?
你是怎么做到的？
How...
史密斯一部分的权限比尼奥和分析师大，其实很好理解
三部曲中这个病毒就无法受建筑师控制，而且决战中史密斯是打倒了尼奥
作为残存的病毒，虽然史密斯不能再无限复制，但依然保留了特工的所有能力
汤姆和我共同点，比你知道的多得多
Tom and I have more in common than you know.
他一脱离矩阵，这么说吧
Once he got out, let's just say,
我就可以做回我自己了
I was free to be me.
-耶  -崔妮蒂？
-Yeah!  -Trinity?
你准备好了吗？
You ready?
是的
Yeah.
【黑猫假说】
纵观四部影片，矩阵被修改的特定地点，一定会有一只黑猫两次经过，可见它是一段架构最底层的程序
而且译者已经确定，这只猫和Matrix 3结尾矩阵大重置、唤醒了萨蒂的那只一模一样，铃铛和链子花纹都没变
在混战如此激烈的情况下，分析师却拼命找它，也许是修改矩阵必须与这只猫产生某种互动\触发（抱着它？）
更有趣的是，结尾崔尼蒂教训分析师的时候，黑猫闻声赶去，却被尼奥抱住，防止分析师作妖修改矩阵
【崔尼蒂成为The One的假说】
是在插入了萨蒂的插头后，崔尼蒂突然力量大增——分析师显然也看出了这一点
三部曲中，先知是The One之母，是她筛选了候选人，再赋予尼奥The One 权限（通过一块cookie，解锁条件是爱）
这里很明显是萨蒂对崔尼蒂做了手脚，应该是注入了The One程序
一个值得思考的事情是：萨蒂从父亲那里继承了复活仓的图纸，为什么就不能继承先知的使命呢？
不要以“片中没说”就否定这一猜测：先知是非常善于选择性告知和撒谎的！萨蒂也理直气壮地对奈奥比隐瞒了尼奥没死的真相
译者认为，萨蒂就是先知的继任者，继续为矩阵制造波动和变革，达到与人类共存的终极目的
她已经有了很多机器子民，再加上人类盟友，已经是城府和实力颇深的一派
哦，不！
Oh, no.
灭了她  灭了她！
Destroy her.  Destroy her!
阻止他们
Stop them.
你以为这就完事了？
You think this is over?
封锁这里  发动“蜂群”
Lockdown.  Initiate swarm.
现在，我们意想不到的联盟结束了
Here, our unexpected alliance ends.
你知道我们的区别在哪吗，汤姆？
You know the difference between us, Tom?
任何人都可能是你
Anyone could have been you.
而我一直都是任何人
Whereas I've always been anyone.
刚才发生了什么？
What just happened?
史密斯的宿主是咖啡师，因为他离现场足够近
什么？
What?
哦不！ 快撤！快撤！
Oh, no!  Move! Move!
快离开那个鬼地方！
Get the hell out of there!
-有多糟？ -就是，最糟的那种
-How bad?  -Like, all the bad.
没错，这真是很糟
Yeah, this is bad.
我想你应该飞不了了吧？
I don't suppose you can still fly?
是的，飞不动了
Yeah, that's not happening.
尼奥！ 快上来
Neo!  Get on.
卡利奥普！ 带走伤员！
Calliope!  Take the wounded!
其他人，我们要和他们待在一起!
Everyone else, we stay with them!
-她怎么样了？  -生命体征良好
-How is she?  -Life signs are good.
她的信号很强，舰长
Her signal's strong, Captain.
干得好，舰长
Well done, Captain.
我们需要的只是一个奇迹
All we need is a miracle.
此处可见，萨蒂知道崔尼蒂会变成救世主，这是她一手策划
我恨机器人
I hate bots.
-把我们弄出去！  -我正在试呢！
-Get us out of here!  -I'm trying!
封锁程序正在跟踪我们  蜂群到处都是
The lockdown is tracking.  Swarm is everywhere.
从没见过这种情况
Never seen anything like this.
希克，那是什么？
Seq, what is that?
怎么了？
What's wrong?
你要干什么？
What are you...
他在把机器人变成人肉炸弹
He's turning bots into bombs.
该死的！
Shit!
莱克西？
Lexy?
谢泼德遇到麻烦了
Sheperd's in trouble.
让我进去吧
Jack me in.
我可以让你进去  但我不知道能不能再让你出来
I can get you in.  I don't know if I can get you out.
不
No!
他们在干什么？
What are they doing?
把他们赶到杀戮区
Herding them into a kill zone.
舰长，你得快点儿了
Captain, you gotta hurry.
撑住啊，莱克西
Hang on, Lex.
莱克西！
Lexy!
他们在那儿！
There they are!
墨菲斯
Morpheus!
莱克西
Lex.
-巴格斯  -太好了
-Bugsy.  -Hell yeah!
希克，尼奥在哪儿？
Seq, where's Neo?
情况很糟  他们被盯住了
It's bad.  They're pinned.
去往屋顶
Heading to a roof.
淋巴结颤动可以是致命的
Nodal fibrillation is critical.
如果再不出来她会死的
She'll die if we don't extract.
崔尼蒂眼中的高楼大厦全是由金色代码构成
译者假说：新IO是人机共建之城，新矩阵也是人机共写——首席设计师就是尼奥
因为无法获得尼奥源代码，分析师便转而让尼奥继续发挥"The One"的root权限为新版矩阵写代码
尼奥办公桌的屏幕上，旧的矩阵即《黑客帝国》，全是绿色代码；新矩阵，即新游戏《二元对立》则充满了金色的建筑物
“免费劳力”尼奥的设计引入了他充沛的自由选择、情感和爱欲，这个越来越真实的矩阵另人们深陷其中不再反抗
为了防止尼奥醒悟逃脱，就用崔尼蒂拖住他，让他们渴望而不可得，还用噩梦警告尼奥，他的脱逃会给挚爱带来伤害
尼奥潜意识里确实怀疑矩阵，但依然自我欺骗了二十年，才终于选择脱离矩阵，他写出模态是自己救了自己
分析师当然也参与编写了新矩阵，而且尼奥（人类）写出的代码是金色，分析师（机器）编写操控的代码是绿色
真是太美了
It's so beautiful.
我想起来了
I remember this.
我想起了我们
I remember us.
在此，我的梦醒了
My dream ended here.
我们不能回去
We can't go back.
我们不会回去
We won't.
他们能跳成功吗？
Can they make the jump?
这不是我干的
I'm not doing this.
这是你干的吗？
Are you doing this?
这一幕没有使用绿幕，而是真的把两位演员吊在城市上空，返璞归真
再见了矩阵
Bye.
真是戏剧式出场
How dramatic.
“蒂芙尼”？
"Tiffany"?
这只是个私下的笑话
It was a private joke.
纯属娱乐，仅此而已
An amusement, that's all.
纯属娱乐？ 嗯
An amusement?  Hmm.
哇哦
Whoa.
就像这样吗？
Kind of like that?
好吧  嗷呜
Okay.  Ow.
如果你这么讨厌这个名字
If you hated the name so much,
那为什么你还一直像个乖巧的小婊子一样沾沾自喜？
why did you heel like a good little bitch so long?
《蒂凡尼的早餐》里的女主是个交际花
是的  这绝对是自找的
Yeah.  Definitely asked for that.
你就不能管管她吗？
Can't you control her?
这是为了你利用了孩子
That was for using children.
我们有几个问题要问
We have a few questions.
你试过激活故障保险系统
You tried to activate the fail-safe.
是我的上司试过
The Suits tried.
显然，因为没掌握你们的源代码
Obviously, without control of your source code,
我知道那是不可能做到的
I knew that was impossible.
那为什么你的上司没有因此清除你呢？
So, why haven't the Suits purged you?
因为我了解这个系统
Because I know the system.
我了解人类
I know human beings.
我也了解你们
And I know you.
现在，你们对自己所做的一切感觉良好
Right now, you're feeling good about what you've done.
这是应该的  好一场胜利  太精彩啦
You should.  It was a victory.  Bravo.
现在呢？
Now what?
你来这里是不是想谈判做个交易？
You've come here to negotiate some kind of deal?
你们以为你们胜券在握
You think you hold all the cards,
因为你可以在这个世界里为所欲为了
because you can do whatever you want in this world.
要我说，那就去呗
I say, go for it.
改造它  去大显身手
Remake it.  Knock yourselves out.
用彩虹描绘天空
Paint the sky with rainbows.
但事实呢
But here's the thing.
羊群哪儿也不会去
The sheeple aren't going anywhere.
sheeple 温顺、顺从、容易被影响的人
他们喜欢我的世界
They like my world.
他们不想要这么多愁善感
They don't want this sentimentality.
他们也不想要自由或是权力
They don't want freedom or empowerment.
他们就想要被控制
They want to be controlled.
他们渴望确定性带来的舒适感
They crave the comfort of certainty.
这就意味着，你们两个，还不如回到培养舱里
And that means you two, back in your pods,
无知觉的，孤零零的，像其他人一样
unconscious and alone, just like them.
我们不是来做什么谈判的
We're not here to negotiate anything.
我们是来重塑你的世界的
We were on our way to remake your world.
改变一些东西
Change a few things.
我有点喜欢“用彩虹描绘天空”的想法
I kind of like the "paint the sky with rainbows" idea.
彩虹 有可能暗含导演对LGTB运动的支持
只是提醒人们自由意志可以做什么
Just remind people what a free mind can do.
我忘了 这很容易忘的
I forgot.  It's easy to forget.
-他很擅长让人忘记这个  -这一点，他还真是的
-He makes it easy. -That, he does.
他真该反省一下了
Something he should think about.
但在我们开始之前，
Before we got started,
我们决定顺道儿说声谢谢
we decided to stop by to say thank you.
你给了我们那些我们从未想过还可以有的东西
You gave us something we never thought we could have.
是什么？
And what is that?
再活一次的机会
Another chance.
致妈妈和爸爸：
爱 是一切的起源
本片拍摄前，导演的父母相继离世，给她们带来了很大的悲痛
面对现实吧，各位  电影已死
Face reality, people.  Movies are dead.
双关，既可视为失去了设计师托马斯后，倒霉的同事们的对话，也可视为“打破第四面墙”与观众对话
游戏已死
Games are dead.
叙事？ 死了
Narrative?  Dead.
媒体上只不过是神经触发的反应
Media is nothing but neuro-trigger response
还有病毒疫情
and viral conditioning.
等等，你们两个到底在说什么？
Wait, what are you two talking about?
猫咪视频
Cat videos.
我们需要的是一系列视频
What we need is a series of videos
我们称之为“猫科帝国”
that we call "The Catrix."